<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian advice both to old and young, rich and poor which may serve as a directory at hand, ready to direct all persons almost in every state and condition. Under XXVII general useful heads.</title>
            <author>Mocket, Thomas, 1602-1670?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 106 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51047</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2303A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217853</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829496</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829496</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33936</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51047)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33936)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1920:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian advice both to old and young, rich and poor which may serve as a directory at hand, ready to direct all persons almost in every state and condition. Under XXVII general useful heads.</title>
                  <author>Mocket, Thomas, 1602-1670?</author>
                  <author>Cross, Thomas, fl. 1632-1682, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 192 p. : ill., port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Edward Brewster, at the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Mocket, who has signed the dedication.</note>
                  <note>Between the  frontispiece portrait and the title page is a leaf which reads: A few verses on Psal. 39. v. 5. Amici cujusdam.</note>
                  <note>Portrait signed: T. Cross sculpsit.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRISTIAN ADVICE Both to OLD and YOUNG, RICH and POOR: Which may ſerve as A DIRECTORY At hand, Ready to direct all Perſons almoſt in every State and Condition. Under XXVII General uſeful Heads.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 10.1.</hi>
               </bibl> Brethren, my hearts deſire to God, and prayer for you all, is that ye may be ſaved.</q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <q>Omne crede diem tibi deluxiſſe ſupremum. <bibl>
                  <hi>Hor.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Si Chriſtum noſcis, nihil eſt ſi caetera neſcis;</l>
                  <l>Si Chriſtum neſcis, nihil eſt ſi caeteta noſcis.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If Chriſt you know, though nothing elſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Twill bring you unto bliſs:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If all things elſe, and know not Chriſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Heaven you ſhall miſs.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edw. Brewſter,</hi> at the <hi>Crane</hi> in <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>engraved portrait of Thomas Mocket by Thomas Cross</figDesc>
                  <byline>T. Croſs ſculpſit</byline>
                  <p>The Effigies of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Tho: Mocket ſome time of Qu: Col: Camb: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: of A: in both the Univerſities and Miniſter of the Goſpel. Aetatis ſuae 68. A:D: 1670.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>The Effigies of the Reverend Author of this Worke M T: M: Haveing knowne him many yeares I thought good to add out of reſpects to him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edw: Brewſter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:4"/>
            <head>A few <hi>VERSES On</hi> Pſal. <hi>39.</hi> v. <hi>5.</hi> Amici cujuſdam.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THreeſcore and ten the age and life of man,</l>
               <l>In holy <hi>Davids</hi> eyes ſeem'd but a ſpan.</l>
               <l>Yet half that time is loſt, and ſpent in ſleep:</l>
               <l>So only thirty five for uſe we keep.</l>
               <l>Our dayes of youth muſt be abated all.</l>
               <l>Child hood and youth wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> doth call</l>
               <l>But vanity, meer vanity he ſaies</l>
               <l>Is what befalls us in our childiſh daies.</l>
               <l>Our daies of age we take no pleaſure in,</l>
               <l>Our daies of grief, we wiſh had never bin.</l>
               <l>So time deducted, youth and age and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</l>
               <l>Only a ſpan is all the time we borrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now we do count our time by years, monthes, dayes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ere long we reckon muſt another wayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Make it your work, here ſo to live and dye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That you may live with God eternally.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Live every day as if it were your laſt day.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:6"/>
            <head>To The Right Honourable, truly Noble and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and now alſo the aged Lady, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Exceter;</hi> increaſe of honour, holineſs and comfort here, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection hereafter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough you might wonder, that ſuch an one as I ſhould preſume to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſo ſmall and mean a piece to your hands, and under your name to the
<pb facs="tcp:33936:7"/>world, who have ſo many rare and excellent Workes of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent men, of your own alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; yet be pleaſed to paſs by my boldneſs, and to accept my Reaſons that moved me ſo to doe, though ſlender. I had ſometimes the honour to wait on, and preach to the Right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lord, <hi>John</hi> Earle of <hi>Bridge-water,</hi> Baron of <hi>Brackly</hi> and <hi>Elſemere, &amp;c.</hi> your Father, and then Lord Preſident of the Marches of <hi>Wales,</hi> under King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, long ſince deceaſed; and had (I may truly ſay without oſtentation) reſpect and favour above my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deſerts, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of preferment. I alſo well knew the Lady <hi>Catherine Courten</hi> your Siſter deceaſed, very worthy to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and honoured, who was
<pb facs="tcp:33936:7"/>pleaſed to accept of a ſmall piece from my hand; alſo your great candor, piety and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which God of his free grace hath inriched you with, for which I cannot but much honour you: and if your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhall be pleaſed to favour a poor Miniſter of Chriſt ſo far, as to let this mean piece come to your hand, and paſs abroad under your Name, though mean and homely; I truſt it may be of ſome uſe to others, and poſſibly to your ſelf, ſeeing the truths of God are the ſame, though in a mean dreſs; and great ſouls must be nouriſhed with the ſame ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere milk of the word, go to Heaven in the ſame plain way of truth and holineſs. Though this be but as Goats hair was, to make an outward covering to ſave the rich Furniture and
<pb facs="tcp:33936:8"/>Curtains of the Tabernacle, and make other rich pieces ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with more luſtre and beauty; this plain homely diſh of ſpiritual food, may give you occaſion to reliſh, value and deſire others the more, and to feed more ſavourly on them. And ſo your Lady ſhip will oblige me to be moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>To love honour, and ſerve you in the Lord, while I am <hi>THO. MOCKET.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:8"/>
            <head>The Contents and principal Heads handled in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>THe Preface</hi> Pag. 1</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Exhortation to ſome to get and exerciſe theſe fundamental Graces</hi> Pag. 4</item>
               <item>1 <hi>Sound Knowledg</hi> Pag. 5</item>
               <item>2 <hi>Saving Faith</hi> Pag. 25</item>
               <item>3 <hi>True Repentance</hi> Pag. 26</item>
               <item>4 <hi>Unfained Live to God and Men</hi> Pag. 27</item>
               <item>5 <hi>Sincere Obedience</hi> Pag. 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Six moving conſiderations to get and grow in thoſe</hi> Pag. 36</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Exhortations and Advices to all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Pag. 41</item>
               <item>1 <hi>To read the Holy Scriptures dally</hi> Pag. 42</item>
               <item>2 <hi>To take and improve the opportunities of hearing</hi> Pag. 45</item>
               <item>3 <hi>To meditate often</hi> Pag. 46</item>
               <item>4 <hi>To be careful to keep holy the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sabbath and Lords-day</hi> Pag. 47</item>
               <item>5 <hi>To pray daily</hi> Pag. 48</item>
               <item>6 <hi>To ſing Pſalms often</hi> Pag. 53</item>
               <item>7 <hi>In performing duties, to be careful to perform them in a right manner, and not to rest in the duty.</hi> Pag. 54</item>
               <item>8 <hi>To obey Magiſtrates</hi> Pag. 56</item>
               <item>9 <hi>To have a lawful Calling, and uſe it lawfully</hi> Pag. 58</item>
               <item>10 <hi>To be watchful to obſerve the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:33936:9"/>and opportunities of doing and receiving good</hi> Pag. 64</item>
               <item>11 <hi>To Charity</hi> Pag. 72</item>
               <item>12 <hi>To them in proſperity</hi> Pag. 75</item>
               <item>13 <hi>To them in adverſity</hi> Pag. 77</item>
               <item>14 <hi>To them under temptations to ſin</hi> Pag. 82</item>
               <item>15 <hi>To ſtudie unity, peace, and love</hi> Pag. 85</item>
               <item>16 <hi>To endeavour to be, and walk always in the fear of the Lord</hi> Pag. 90</item>
               <item>17 <hi>To ſtudy to carry themſelves affably, courteouſly, and neighbourly to all</hi> Pag. 104</item>
               <item>18 <hi>Uſe a moderation in all things, at all times, and to all perſons</hi> Pag. 106</item>
               <item>19 <hi>Study and endeavour to be good and uſeful in all relations</hi> Pag. 112</item>
               <item>20 <hi>To uſe recreations when nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, lawfully and wiſely</hi> Pag. 114</item>
               <item>21 <hi>To think often, and prepare for death</hi> Pag. 115</item>
               <item>22 <hi>To marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>generally</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>particularly</hi> to
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Husbands</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Wives</hi> Page. 118</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>23 <hi>To Parents</hi> Pag. 130</item>
               <item>24 <hi>To Children</hi> Pag. 139</item>
               <item>25 <hi>To Maſters and Governours of Families</hi> Pag. 153</item>
               <item>26 <hi>To Servants</hi> Pag. 160</item>
               <item>27 <hi>To them that are poor</hi> Pag. 173</item>
               <item>28 <hi>Some Objections anſwered</hi> Pag. 177</item>
               <item>29 <hi>The Concluſion, with ſome choice Scriptures.</hi> Pag. 188</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33936:9"/>
            <head>To <hi>My dear Relations, Friends and Acquaintance, eſpecially in the Counties of</hi> Kent, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Middleſex, Hertford <hi>and</hi> Eſſex. T. M. <hi>heartily wiſheth Grace, Mercy and Peace, from God the Father, and from our Lord Jeſus Christ, with a daily encreaſe thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>DEAR FRIENDS:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu have been loving, kind and reſpective unto me and mine; and now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Aged, drawing near unto ſeventy, I am very deſirous to leave with you a few lines, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a worldly Legacy, (which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33936:10"/>I am ſure many of you need not, nor deſire) as a Teſtimony of my thankfulneſs, unfeigned love, due reſpects, and hearty deſire of your real good, temporal and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal: that they may be preſent with you, and ſpeak unto you, when I cannot come at you, or am gone from you into the place of ſilence: and therefore I have been deſirous to publiſh theſe lines; (the ſubſtance of which, for the moſt part, being the fruit of ſome hours thoughts in my bed,) and in a very plain phraſe and method, being intended for the meaneſt and weakeſt capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as well as others. And though it be but as Goats-hair towards the building of the Tabernacle, yet notwithſtanding may, (and I hope in the Lord, will, through his bleſſing) help alſo others memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſtir up their affections and hearts to a more ſerious walking in the good way of holineſs and righteouſneſs; which will bring to heaven, and eternal happineſs. Into which way, I am fully perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33936:10"/>many of you are already entred and walking; but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay ſo of all to whom this is intended and offer'd, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hope you will not be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, though I do adde divers directions for the better informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, inſtruction, and direction of others, towards the more eaſie getting, preſerving and increaſing ſound knowledge, true and living grace, to enable for the right uſe of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, too much neglected by many, and all other Ordinances of Chriſt: and eſpecially to be prepared to live and dye holily, comfortably, and happily; which, next to the glorifying of God, is the great buſineſs which we have all to do, while we are here in this world, and for which end we came into the world, and God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us life, the uſe of reaſon, and underſtanding, and the Word and Sacraments, the means of grace and ſalvation; which if any do neglect, they are utterly and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly undone, and muſt periſh
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33936:11"/>eternally. But rather I judge it will be a rejoycing of hearts to you, who are already made wiſe unto ſalvation, to ſee or hear that others alſo that are made wiſe, or any ways helped in the way to get true wiſdom.</p>
            <p>I intended this only as an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to another Treatiſe on a neceſſary ſubject; but ſeeing it ſwell in the penning, very much beyond my expectation, I pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it by it ſelf, and it may be the other hereafter, if life, health, liberty, and the croud of other mens workes, that preſs to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, do not hinder.</p>
            <p>There are divers qualifications and things required, as abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary to them of years of diſcretion, to be had and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed; as to be enabled rightly to partake of the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper as a priviledge and benefit, ſo to live and dye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably and happily, which is the earneſt deſire of my ſoul, and daily prayer unto God for you all: namely, ſound know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33936:11"/>of the things of God, ſaving faith, true repentance, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere love and charity, and new o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, or holineſs of heart and life: and therefore I intend to ſpeak ſomething of each of them ſeverally, by the aſſiſtance of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Knowledge,</hi> a particular di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct grounded knowledge is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation, in all that are of years of diſcretion. Let me mind ſome of you, of ſome of the moſt neceſſary points of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, the doctrine which is according to godlineſs. Namely, that there is only one true and living God, and three diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or manner of ſubſiſting in that one undivided divine nature and Godhead; the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> or <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That there is a God.</hi> Becauſe we live in an Age, in which that damning ſin of unbelief and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm is much more frequent then (I think) in any Age hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore amongſt Chriſtians, a ſad ſign that ſome grievous judgment from God, if not deſtruction, is drawing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33936:12"/>near: I ſhall here ſet down a few Arguments, to prove, <hi>That there is a God,</hi> (which a man would think moſt clear, and needs no proving) which I hope may be of ſome uſe to confirm many; though not to convince profeſſed Atheiſts, or wilful Cavillers.</p>
            <p>Beſides the Teſtimony of the holy Scriptures (which have many demonſtrative arguments in them, to prove cleerly the divinity and infallible verity and certainty of the holy Scripture, and ſo moſt fully and plainly that there is a God; conſider ſeriouſly theſe few of many that might be produced.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Heavens and Earth, and all the Creatures in them, as the Sun, Moon, Starrs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do clearly prove it, to all that are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blind, and judicially given up to blindneſs, to their eternal deſtruction: <q rend="inline">for nothing can be the cauſe of it ſelf; the world could not make it ſelf, for then it ſhould be both the cauſe and the effect, both before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſelf. Therefore the world
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33936:12"/>and all things in it muſt have their being and beginning from ſome one firſt and ſupream cauſe, which is of infinite wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, power and goodneſs, and of it ſelf; which gives being and continuance to all other things: and this is God.</q>
            </p>
            <q>Alſo the firſt creature was made of nothing, of no forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exiſtant matter; otherwiſe if not made, it could not be ſubject to change and alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And all Creatures are finite, compounded, and imperfect unable to make themſelves, or the leaſt fly, or worm, or to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain themſelves; and therefore of neceſſity, there muſt be a firſt ſupream cauſe, which is of it ſelf, of infinite power, wiſdome, and goodneſs, and moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, which gives a being and continuance to that firſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to all things, which are very good in their kind, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31.</q>
            <p n="2">2. The great wonders and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles that have been done, as the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33936:13"/>dividing the red Sea and <hi>Jordan,</hi> cauſing the Sun and Moon to ſtand ſtill, and at another time to go back ten degrees; and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles wrought by the Prophets, by Chriſt himſelf and the Apoſtles, as raiſing the dead, making them that were born blind to ſee, the lame to go, the dumb to ſpeak, the dead to live again, and very many more, which many thouſands of eye and ear-witneſſes ſaw &amp; heard; all which were not only above the ordinary courſe of nature, but ſimply above the power of nature: do plainly and evidently prove, that there is one ſupream abſolute cauſe, of infinite knowledge, power and goodneſs, which is God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The acts of conſcience do prove that there is a God; which are to excuſe and comfort in well doing, againſt diſgraces, ſlanders, and ſufferings; and to accuſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne and terrify for evil doing, though committed never ſo ſecret, and ſo that ſomtimes the ſinners to free themſelves of the terrous &amp; troubles of conſcience make away
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33936:13"/>themſelves; thouſands have done ſo in all Ages: which proves that there is a ſupream Judge that ſees all, though never ſo ſecret, will call the ſinners to account, and condemne for their evil deeds, and puniſh the evil doers.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The powers of the Soul prove,</hi> that there is a God. The Soul is a ſubſtance ſpiritual, inviſible, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, ever-living, exceeding active, that can move its thoughts and eyes from one place to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from one kingdome and part of the world to another, from earth to heaven in a moment; is indued with underſtanding, will, reaſon and affection, and is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of eternal happineſs, and of eternal miſery; and therefore muſt of neceſſity be from a cauſe that is ſpiritual, inviſible, immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, infinite in underſtanding, wiſdom, power and goodneſs, which only can ſatisfie the vaſt and boundleſs deſires of the Soul: which cauſe is God; for the Soul could not make it ſelf, and its admirable faculties.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33936:14"/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The practices of Satan prove as much:</hi> for the devil labours by all means to move men to deny God, to draw them to ſin, and all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs, to extinguiſh the light of the word, and to keep men in ignorance, bring them into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, prophaneſs and all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; as our preſent times and all Ages prove by woful experience; and ſo to bring men to eternal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: which plainly ſhews that there is a God, who is moſt holy, juſt, good, and that gives eternal life to his children &amp; ſervants that deſire faithfully to ſerve him, keep his law, and obey his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>John</hi> 10.27, 28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The conſent of all Nations in the world</hi> prove clearly that there is a God; no Nation was ever ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous as not to acknowledge and worſhip a God, as the Heathen O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator <hi>Cicero</hi> obſerved: &amp; although they could not by the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture know the true God; yet they had and worſhipped many Gods, or Idols rather, yea ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, as <hi>Acts</hi> 17.23. <hi>To the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33936:14"/>God,</hi> that they might be ſure amongſt them all to worſhip the true God: a plain &amp; ſure argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they knew there is a God to whom divine worſhip is due.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>The defence, protection and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Church and people of God,</hi> who were very few at the firſt, notwithſtanding all the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, fury, power and policy of the Devil, and all worldly men his inſtruments, who were very many to one Chriſtian, and thoſe many of them of great Authority, malice, power and policy; and laboured with all their might, by all means poſſible that the Devil and worldly men could invent, utterly to root out all that did own and profeſs Jeſus Chriſt, and the Chriſtian Religion; as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. Notwithſtanding the Chriſtians have been wonderfully preſerved, defended, ſupported and ſtrengthned to indure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, diſgrace, poverty, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the moſt exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that could be invented, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33936:15"/>to the death, with invincible courage, and admirable patience, comfort and cheerfulneſs alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, &amp; were much increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the very ſame means the Enemies uſed to root them out: and the Enemies were plagued with dreadful judgements, and horrors of conſcience; ſo that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, out of anguiſh and deſpair of attaining their ends, the deſtruction of the Church, made away themſelves, others did leave their places of great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, power, wealth and honour: which is an evident demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that there is a God of infinite power, wiſdom, goodneſs and juſtice, that did ſo defend, protect, ſupport, comfort and multiply his ſuffering people, and diſappoint, plague and ſeverely puniſh their Enemies, that they might eaſily ſee their ſin in their puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Laſtly, to name no more, it is an evident and undeniable ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that there is a God, that ſuch as have ſtudied to become A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, could never blot this truth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33936:15"/>out of their conſciences, but at ſome times were forced to confeſs that there is a God, at leaſt to fear and tremble at the thoughts of his Majeſty, and wonderful workes, as thunder, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That there is but one God,</hi> is evident to common reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there can be but one infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, omnipotent, eternal and moſt perfect being; but one firſt cauſe of all things, for all things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to one firſt cauſe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.35. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.8. and 4.11.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That there are three diſtinct perſons</hi> or manners of ſubſiſting, in that one God-head. That there is a plurality of divine perſons, more then one, is evident from the Hebrew forms of ſpeaking of God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. In the original, word for word, <hi>Gods he created;</hi> a Noun plural, to a Verb ſingular. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.5. <hi>Thy makers is thy hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.</hi> Eccles. 12.1. <hi>Remember thy Creators.</hi> So, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 149.2. Alſo <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 19.24. <hi>Jehovah rained up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorrha <hi>brimstone and fire,</hi> from <hi>Jehovah</hi> out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33936:16"/>likewiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Let us make man. Job</hi> 35.10. Theſe and divers other Hebrew forms and expreſſions, prove that there is a plurality of perſons, of divine perſons in the God-head. That there is a Trinity, three diſtinct divine perſons in the God-head, is clearly evidenced, (and ſo as cannot with any colour of reaſon be denyed) from thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Alſo from 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>There are three that beare record in Heaven; the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one;</hi> namely, one God. See likewiſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16, 17.</p>
            <p>Which three divine perſons in that one undivided eſſence, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or God-head, are theſe; the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> or <hi>Spirit;</hi> and are all co-equal, co-eſſential and co-eternal, of a moſt pure and ſpiritual na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, infinite in underſtanding, wiſdom, power, goodneſs, mercy;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33936:16"/>moſt holy, and moſt righteous.</p>
            <p>That God is the creator, maker, preſerver, and governour of the whole world, and of all perſons and things in it, with all their actions and events: that he made man after his own Image, in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, righteouſneſs, and true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; who by eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, loſt the Image of God, in which he was created, and all his peace and happineſs, and all mankind in him, and became very ſinful and miſerable of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by nature altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to do any thing that is truly and ſpiritually good and pleaſing unto God, or not to do evil, which brings guilt and condemnation.</p>
            <p>That Jeſus Chriſt, the eternal Son of God, the ſecond Perſon in <hi>the bleſſed Trinity,</hi> took on him the nature of man, and was made in all things like unto us, ſin only excepted; was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> ſuffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate;</hi> and ſo on as it is in the Creed: and this, that in our nature, name and ſtead, he might fulfil the law, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33936:17"/>Gods juſtice, and purchaſe for all, his righteouſneſs and life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal.</p>
            <p>Alſo, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Prophet, Prieſt and King of his Church.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Prophet,</hi> to reveal unto us the way to everlaſting life, what we are to know, believe, and do that we might be eternally ſaved. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.18, 19. <hi>John</hi> 6.14. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18, 19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he is <hi>a Prieſt,</hi> and our great high Prieſt, to offer up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a ſacrifice once for all, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.1. and 9.26. Which he did by his ſuffering death, and riſing again to ſatisfie the juſtice and law of God for mans ſins in tranſgreſſing his law, and thereby purchaſing for all his eternal redemption, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, forgiveneſs of ſins, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, acceptation of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and ſervices, and eternal life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. and all good things needful for this life, and that to come; and alſo to make interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Father for us. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>Chriſt is alſo a King,</hi> to bridle and ſubdue all his Enemies,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33936:17"/>
               <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1, 2. and ſo gather &amp; govern his Elect and choſen; powerfully to ſave them out of the hand and power of ſin, Satan, death and hell; bring them into his Church and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by effectual calling and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, and to govern them by his word and ſpirit to life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. <hi>John</hi> 10.16. <hi>Haggai</hi> 2 7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Alſo, there muſt be a particular and diſtinct knowledge in ſome meaſure of the moral law of God, and of the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the law of God,</hi> a brief ſum of which we have contained in the Decalogue or Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; which contains the duty we doe owe to God and Man; what is evil, and what we are to repent of, ſhun and avoid, and what we are to do and practice; how we are to carry our ſelves, both towards God in all duties of piety and holineſs; and towards man, our ſelves and others, in the duties of mercy, juſtice and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33936:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33936:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33936:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sacraments</hi> alſo. There muſt be a particular knowledge of the Sacraments of the new Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> Baptiſm &amp; the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is a Sacrament of our ingrafting into Chriſt, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him, and entrance into the Church. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4. <hi>It ſignifies</hi> the waſhing away of ſin from the Soul by the blood of Chriſt, and the renewing graces of his Spirit; and ſo our juſtification and forgiveneſs of ſinnes, and our ſanctification, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. <hi>Titus</hi> 3.5. <hi>And binds</hi> all that have been baptized, to believe in Chriſt, forſake ſin, and live holy according to the command of God. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37, 38. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baptiſm it a priviledge</hi> which belongs to all the Infants of believing Chriſtian Parents. <hi>Mark</hi> 10.13, 14. When ſome would have hindred the Parents from bringing their young children to Chriſt to bleſs them, his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples rebuked thoſe that brought them: <hi>but when Jeſus ſaw it,,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33936:19"/>he was much diſpleaſed, and ſaid, Suffer little children to come unto me, and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the kingdom of God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of theſe and ſuch like, is the kingdome of God.</hi> If little children, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, Children new borne, as <hi>Luke</hi> hath it, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.15. be within the Covenant, as they are; then they ought to have the Seal of the Covenant; and if they be of Gods kingdome, his ſubjects, then they muſt wear his Livery and badge. Infants are now as capable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Baptiſm and the benefits of it, as the Infants of the Jews were to receive Circumciſion: and what is now objected againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſm, might as well have been alleadged againſt the Jews circumciſing their children: therefore to lay aſide or deny In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſm to the children of believing Chriſtians, is in effect to make themſelves wiſer then God. I will add but one argument.</p>
            <p>That which was commanded and practiſed by the people of God, for two thouſand years, yea
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33936:20"/>and much more, was approved and commanded of God, and is no where forbidden or repealed, is ſtill to be uſed; but the ſealing of the Infants of believers with the firſt ſeal of the Covenant, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, practiſed by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God ſo long, alſo approved and commanded of God; and 'tis no where repealed or forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſhew it if any can: therefore it is ſtill a duty to be obſerved by Chriſtian believing Parents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> It is objected, that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſm is no where comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the new Teſtament, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny expreſs example; and we muſt do nothing without divine war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> True: but this is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent warrant: to give the firſt ſeal of the Covenant to Infants, was expreſly commanded in the old Teſtament, and is no where re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed or forbidden; therefore a duty ſtill, as the obſervation of the Lords day, or Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath is by the fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Beſides, there are expreſs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33936:20"/>general commands to baptize In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants in the New Teſtament, as, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 39. and general examples of whole houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds; and 'tis much more then probable, there were many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in them, let them prove the contrary if they can: men had need to have cleer &amp; expreſs Scripture, to lay aſide a duty commanded and approved of God, &amp; ſo long practiſed by the godly, by the whole Church of God. It troubles me to ſee and hear that any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing godlineſs ſhould be ſo far deceived, and be ſo injurious to themſelves, &amp; their poor Infants, as to deny to give them that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and favour, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly Chriſt allows and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, whoſe grace and priviledges are not leſs to the children un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, then to them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, but rather much more. That place moſt think is full, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. The Gentiles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ingrafted into the true Olive-tree, do partake of the root and fatneſs of the Olive-tree, of all the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33936:21"/>priviledges of the Jews, the true Church of God, whereof <hi>Abraham</hi> was the root and father; of which to be within the Covenant, to be members of the Church of God, and have the firſt Seal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which now is baptiſm, is one; and when they come to years, the Sacrament of the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per alſo. I will add but this. If Chriſt under the Goſpel hath barred Infants of believing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, then it is, either in mercy or in judgement: let them that deny Infant-Baptiſm, make their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, &amp; I know readily what to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; But I now ſtudy brevity, brief hints onely, not large treatiſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Sacrament of the Lords Supper</hi> is alſo an ordinance inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuded by Jeſus Chriſt, in the ſame night in which he was betrayed, to be a Sacrament of our continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and growth in Chriſt; to repreſent and ſignifie the body and blood of Chriſt crucifyed for our ſins, together with all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of his ſuffering and death,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33936:21"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. and 11.23, 24, 25, 26. To be a ſpecial token and pledge of his great love, in ſuffering and dying for loſt and miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and enemies. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>The end is to confirm our faith in Chriſt, communion with him, and all ſaving graces in us, (but it cannot confirm theſe, where they are not) to keep in remembrance the Lords death until he come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and to teſtify our love one to another. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and all other grounds and principles, of the Chriſtian Religion, at leaſt thoſe which are abſolutely neceſſary to life and ſalvation, muſt be known and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood: for without a particular diſtinct knowledge of theſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of faith and godlineſs, in ſome meaſure, there can be neither ſaving faith, nor repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, nor love, nor holineſs in truth, without which there can be no ſalvation. <hi>John</hi> 17.3. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.11. <hi>This is life eternal, to know thee the only true, God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33936:22"/>thou haſt ſent.</hi> Prov. 19.2. <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge the minde is not good.</hi> Hoſ. 4.6. <hi>My people are deſtroyed for lack of knowledg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Particularly,</hi> concerning the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament conſider 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27, 29. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall eat this bread, and drink this cup of the Lord unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is guilty of the body and blood of the Lord, and eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelf.</hi> (Mark the reaſon in the next words) <hi>not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lords body.</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from heaven with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, taking ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with everlaſting deſtruction.</hi> And ſo on to <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>And this knowledge muſt not be an idle meer notional know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, ſwimming in the brain; but an operative, practical, powerful, transforming knowledge, ſuch as workes on the heart, and puts on to believe and practice what a man knoweth; and doth tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33936:22"/>change, and make a man to endeavour to be like unto God himſelf; loving, merciful, good, gratious, holy, juſt, true and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. Many wicked men, yea, enemies and perſecutors of the true Religion and godly men, have &amp; do know much as to a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative and notional knowledge; and can ſpeak well, when they pleaſe, but make no conſcience to practice what they know.</p>
            <p>Secondly. <hi>Faith</hi> is neceſſary to the right participation of the Lords Supper, alſo to live and die comfortably and happily. A par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diſtinct <hi>Faith, which is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieving and reſting on Chriſt alone for ſalvation, as he is offered to us in the Goſpel.</hi> More largely and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, <hi>Faith is a reſting and rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on God the Father, for all good things, both for ſoul and body, this life and that to come, only for the alone mercy of God, and merit of Chriſt, the Mediatour.</hi> John 1.12. and 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſe believeth in him ſhould not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33936:23"/>periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> Mark 16.16. <hi>He that believeth— ſhall be ſaved, but he that believeth not ſhall be damned.</hi> Heb. 11.6. <hi>Without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Repentance</hi> is alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to live and die well, and happily. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3.5. Said our Saviour, <hi>Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> Therefore it is called <hi>Repentance unto life,</hi> Acts 11.18. Now <hi>repentance is a conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or turning of the heart and whole man from ſin, (all ſin in affection and endeavour) unto God.</hi> Therefore it is ſo often expreſſed in the Scripture by <hi>turning;</hi> as <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.30. and 30.10. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.35. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.12. and very often elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <p>There are two parts of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; Humiliation, and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Humiliation and ſorrow for ſin</hi> paſt and preſent, becauſe ſin, a tranſgreſſion of the holy juſt and good law of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. and becauſe offenſive and hateful to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33936:23"/>God; a filthy thing, defiling and dangerous to our ſelves, yea dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable if continued in.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reformation</hi> or amendment of life, an unfained leaving of all ſin in affection, and alſo in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, in reſpect of ſincere deſires, purpoſe and endeavour daily to amend whatſoever is amiſs, and to lead a life according to the command of God; without which ſorrow for ſin and humiliation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes little.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, ſincere love,</hi> true hearty Chriſtian love is another neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grace; both love to God the Father, Jeſus Chriſt, and to our Neighbour.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Love to God, even the whole bleſſed Trinity in unity, who is the only chief and all-ſufficient good, moſt lovely in reſpect of his moſt excellent wiſdome, love, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, holineſs, mercy, truth, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, juſtice, and all other his tranſcendent perfections. Alſo for what he hath done for us, and is ſtill moſt ready to do for his people <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt love
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33936:24"/>the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, with all thy ſoul, and with all thy might.</hi> So <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt love our Neighbour alſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37. <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf;</hi> that is, truly, heartily and really, making it appear by the fruits and effects of it, as occaſion requireth, and opportunity ſerveth, and as we are able, and that both to good and bad men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Good men with a love of complacency and delight, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Image of God in them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Bad men, evil, yea wicked men, yea, enemies, with a love of benevolence, that is, ſo as to pity them, wiſh them good, pray for them, counſel, inſtruct, admoniſh and reprove alſo, when there is juſt cauſe, occaſion, opportunity, and we may do it with any hopes of doing good. <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart, but thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy neighbour, &amp; not ſuffer ſin upon him,</hi> or not bear ſin for him, as the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33936:24"/>margin hath it. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5 44. <hi>I ſay unto you,</hi> (ſaid the Lord Jeſus) <hi>Love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which deſpitefully uſe you, and perſecute you, that you may be the children of your Father which is in heaven.</hi> Not rendring evil for evil, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. Yet hate and ſhun their ſins, and <hi>have no fellowſhip in the unfruitful workes of darkneſs,</hi> Eph. 5.11.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, ſincere obedience, an hearty deſire, purpoſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to obſerve the whole will of God, and obey him in all his commands both of piety and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards God, and of juſtice, equity and mercy towards men, &amp; ſobriety towards ones ſelf, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. This I mention particularly, though it might have been inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the former, becauſe Chriſt will be a Saviour to none but to them that do ſincerely obey him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. Chriſt Jeſus ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from heaven, with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, rendring vengeance on them that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33936:25"/>know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9, 10. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would have it particularly minded and obſerved,</p>
            <p>Now conſider, I beſeech you, for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, and that ſeriouſly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether you have theſe, ſuch a knowledge of God, and of your ſelves; whether you do in ſome meaſure ſee your miſery by ſin, the remedy thereof by Chriſt; know the doctrine of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that not with a bare notional knowledg, but a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and practical knowledg. And have you a true living faith in God, through Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent? ſuch a faith as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the righteouſneſs of Chriſt for juſtification, and draws virtue from him for ſanctification and holy converſation? Do you truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of your ſins, and heartily endeavour to amend what is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs? are you new creatures, and endeavour to live in newneſs of life? Do you mak conſcience of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33936:25"/>obeying Gods commands, of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving holily, and dealing truly, faithfully and juſtly with all men? Do you truly love God for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and above all things, and your neighbour truly and heartily for Gods and Chriſts ſake, wiſhing his good, and be ready to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtian neighbourly office of love for him, or any of them; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving private wrongs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, as you would that God for Chriſts ſake ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give you? or do you heartily deſire and truly endeavour after theſe things? if ſo in truth, then happy are you, bleſſed be God for this great mercy and goodneſs to you: he has done more for you, then if he had given you very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands, and made you great, the greateſt perſons in the world, yea, then if he had given you all the world; when he has left ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, even great ones, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to live and dye in their ſins, and periſh in their ignorance, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief and impenitency. The Lord increaſe it in you daily more and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33936:26"/>more where it is begun, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve you to his heavenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>But if you be ſtill groſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or in your unbelief and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency, you (ſo many of you as ſo continue) are in the ſtate of nature, in the gall of bitterneſs, without Chriſt, ſervants to ſin, ſlaves to the Devil, children of wrath; and ſo living and dying, muſt periſh eternally. Give me leave therefore plainly to tell you the truth, for you will finde it ſo, and no way poſſible of eſcaping the wrath to come; if you will not believe me, read your ſelves <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.16. <hi>The wicked and all that forget God, ſhall be turned into Hell,</hi> that is, all that do not ſo know God as to remember him, and obey his command. Read alſo <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.6. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9, 10. Then</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider, the abſolute neceſſity of divine knowledg in ſome degre; of faith, repentance, love to God and men, of ſincere obedience to his commands, and of holyneſs, unto life and ſalvation. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33936:26"/>knowledge of the doctrine of the Goſpel, and law alſo in ſome meaſure, there can be no true faith, nor repentance, nor love, nor true obedience, nor holyneſs, of heart and life; no juſtification no pardon, or forgiveneſs of ſins, nor any true peace, or comfort, in life nor death, neither here nor hereafter. To this end, I beſeech you read and conſider ſeriouſly theſe and other ſuch like places of Scripture, though ſome of them have been mentioned already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>viz.</hi> concerning the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> John 17.3. Hoſ. 4.6. 2 Theſ. 1.7, 8, 9. Of <hi>Faith,</hi> John 3.16. Mark 16.16. Of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> Luk. 13.3, 5. Ezek. 18.30, 31. <hi>Of new obedience to God, of righteouſneſs and holineſs</hi> of heart and life, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8, 27. and 22.14, 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. and 6.7, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider your miſerable condition without ſome meaſure of knowledge, faith, and other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving graces, and holyneſs. If you be deſtitute of theſe, and ſo go on
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33936:27"/>ſtill in your ignorance, or unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and impenitency, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the commands of God, there will be no hope, or poſſibility; you ſhall for ever be ſhut out of Heaven, deprived of Gods favour, health, peace, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, eaſe, and of all worldly good things, of every good thing that may afford you any the leaſt joy, comfort, eaſe or content: more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, you cannot, ſo living and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, eſcape being condemned and turned into hell, when you dye, there to be tormented for ever, with the Devil and the damned ſpirits (read and conſider in the fear of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41, 46.) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hope of an end, releaſe, eaſe or mitigation, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.10, 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.23, 24, 25, 26. <hi>They ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture into the cup of his indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and they ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb: &amp; the ſmoake of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſcendeth up for ever and ever:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33936:27"/>&amp; they have no reſt day nor night:</hi> O woful! that word of being tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ever and ever, is the moſt tranſcendent aſtoniſhing thing; the very fore-ſight, or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of it, is very dreadful to them that have their conſciences any whit awakened. See <hi>Iſai.</hi> 33.14. <hi>The ſinners in</hi> Zion <hi>were afraid, fearfulneſs ſurprized them,</hi> (ſo that they cryed out) <hi>Who among us ſhall dwell with the devouring fire? who among us ſhall dwell with everlaſting burnings?</hi> If the ſight or thought of it, at ſo great a diſtance, was ſo dreadful, as that nothing run in their minds and mouthes, but <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring fire, and everlasting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;</hi> what will the torment it ſelf be when felt? and if the pain of one member here tormented with the gout, ſtone, head-ach, tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach, cholick, or the like, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be ſo grievous, eſpecially when in an high degree, which u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually is but for a few hours or dayes at moſt; what will the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell be, which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue not onely for a few daies, or
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33936:28"/>years, but for very very many thouſand and hundred thouſands of years, yea for ever and ever, never to have any end, or any the leaſt eaſe, or mitigation of pain; no not after millions and milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of years. You know the ſad ſtory or parable of the rich glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after death, was caſt into hell, and being in great torments, could not obtain ſo much water to cool his tongue, as would hang on the tip of ones finger; no not of merciful <hi>Abraham</hi> his Father, as he truly called him, according to the fleſh. The Lord help you and I, ſeriouſly to conſider this, ſo as to prevent it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider how long you have lived, how much of your time is ſpent already, how uncertain your life is, how ſhort it may be, and how ſuddenly death may come on you. Many in the world, yea ſome which many of us have known, have been alive and well in the morning, and dead ere night; and ſome that have gone to bed well,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33936:28"/>were the next morning dead: and of ſome alive, well, ill, and dead in a few houres. I ſhall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately minde you of one, whom divers of you and my ſelf very well knew, an antient Gentleman of very good parts, that in harveſt laſt 1669, was in good health, ſupt very well, was very cheerful and lively, walked abroad after ſupper, his wife &amp; one or two more being preſent, fell down ſuddenly dead, without ſo much as giving a groan or ſigh. And as death ſuddenly befell him, ſo it may do any of us, that ſurvive. <hi>Oh that they were wiſe,</hi> (ſaid God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29.) <hi>that they understood this, that they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their latter end!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if any will not hearken to God, repent and return to him, but go on ſtill in ſin, preſuming on the mercy of God; how juſt may it be with God, and what cauſe is there to fear, that he will not hereafter give them time to repent, or elſe not give them the means, or if both time and means, yet not the grace to uſe that time
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33936:29"/>and means, ſo as to repent to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, who have and do willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglect the preſent time and means! We all know well enough that God himſelf hath ſaid, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.24, 25, 26, to 32. <hi>Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed; I have ſtretched out my hand, and no man regarded,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I alſo will laugh at your calamity, I will mock when your fear cometh as a whirl-wind, when diſtreſs and anguiſh cometh upon you. Then ſhall they call upon me, but</hi> I <hi>will not anſwer, they ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall not finde me: for that they hated knowledg, and did not chuſe the fear of the Lord. They would none of my counſel, they deſpiſed all my reproof: therefore ſhall they eat of the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true indeed, one ſinner (we read of, the good Thief on the Croſs) repented at his laſt hour, and found mercy; but we do not read of any more in the whole Bible that did ſo: and his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was miraculous, and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33936:29"/>to confirm the truth of Chriſts doctrine, calling and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to be the Meſſiah and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: one, that none who, through ignorance or neglect, have put off repentance, might deſpair; and yet but one, that none might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> well obſerved.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conſider how abſurd, how unjuſt, and unreaſonable it is, that any ſhould give the firſt &amp; beſt of their days, wit, parts and ſtrength to the ſervice of ſin, the world and the Devil, as all natural, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate and impenitent men and women do, and the laſt and worſt of their parts and abilities to God, when they can do little or nothing for God; who in all reaſon and upon everlaſting obligations, ſhould have the firſt, beſt, laſt, and all the time and abilities they have. It is our duty to give all to him, and his due, upon moſt weighty conſiderations, as of his creating us of nothing, preſerving, ſuſtaining with food, rayment, in health, peace; and alſo by our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn engagement at Baptiſme to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33936:30"/>be the Lords, renewed at the Lords ſupper, vows in our ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, weakneſſes, ſtreights and dangers: would any of us be willing to be ſo ſerved by any one, that hath his dependance, and all he hath from us?</p>
            <p n="6">6. I beſeech you in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and as you tender the everlaſting good of your ſoules and bodies, if any of you have neglected this great and moſt neceſſary work, to uſe all the good means appointed of God, with all ſpeed and ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for the getting and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſound knowledg, ſaving faith, true repentance, ſincere love, real obedience, and holineſs of heart and life, of which I ſhall ſpeak more in the general conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations and advices immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly following, which I hope may be of ſome uſe to all ſorts and ranks of men.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>(my dear friends and acquaintance)</hi> let me in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of Jeſus Chriſt, be your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer,</hi> to put you in minde
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33936:30"/>of, and quicken you in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of theſe few following, profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, neceſſary and comfortable Chriſtian exerciſes, though you do know them already, and are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in them, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> did his beloved Chriſtians, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12, 13. <hi>I will not be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to put you alwayes in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of theſe things, though you know them, and be eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth. Yea I think it meet as long as I am in this Tabernacle, to ſtir you up by putting you in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, knowing that ſhortly. I muſt put off this my tabernacle, even as our Lord Jeſus Christ hath ſhewed me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I will mind you of no other thing, then what I my ſelf deſire, really, ſincerely, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to practice: and Oh that the good Lord would inable me by his grace, and that you would help me by your prayers! for I aſſure you, I deſire to think of you alwayes, and to minde you, in my approaches unto God. Oh my friends, my heart is inlarged to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, and for you; be you
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33936:31"/>alſo enlarged to God for me: I have great need of your prayers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Read the holy Scriptures daily,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> the <hi>Epistles</hi> of the Apoſtles, and the book of <hi>Pſalms;</hi> and let ſuch as cannot read themſelves, get them read as often as they can. Even Kings, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their many other great and weighty imployments for the publick good, muſt <hi>have a copy of the holy Scriptures by them, and read therein all the dayes</hi> (that is, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day) <hi>of their lives, that they may learn to fear the Lord their God, and to keep all the words of the Law and the Statutes, and do them,</hi> Deut. 17.18, 19. <hi>For bleſſed is the man that delighteth in the Law of the Lord, and in his Law doth meditate day and night,</hi> Pſal. 1.2.</p>
            <p>And in reading the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, obſerve, as well as you can, 1. What ſins are forbidden, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned or puniſhed, to avoid them. 2. What duties command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, commended or approved, to obſerve and doe them. 3. What promiſes are made, and to whom,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33936:31"/>and believe them, apply them, reſt on them, for your encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in well doing, or avoiding evil. 4. What threatnings there are againſt any ſin, or judgements of God or man on ſinners, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the ſins. And 5. what bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are on the godly, or good things he has done for any, to comfort and encourage you in well doing.</p>
            <p>There are alſo many other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent books, and treatiſes, on ſeveral parts of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: alſo on particular neceſſary Chriſtian duties, of ſingular uſe to inſtruct and direct a Chriſtian in every duty of his general and particular calling, alſo in every particular ſtate, condition, and relation; which are worth your reading, and ſerious peruſal: which you ſhall do very well to redeem what time you can conveniently, to read and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on them. I ſhall, for their ſakes that know not, name a few choice books; as <hi>the Practice of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Mr.</hi> Scudders <hi>daily walk with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33936:32"/>God; Mr.</hi> Balls <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> with the expoſition and <hi>treatiſe of living by faith; Mr.</hi> Baxters <hi>call to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted,</hi> alſo his book intituled, <hi>Now or Never; Dr.</hi> Gouge <hi>of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestical duties; Mr.</hi> Thomas Gouge <hi>his word to Sinners and Saints; Mr.</hi> Dod <hi>on the Ten Commandments; Mr.</hi> Burroughs <hi>Jewel of content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Mr.</hi> Gurnaſs <hi>whole armour of God,</hi> on <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. in three parts; <hi>Mr.</hi> Fenner <hi>of Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Gods alarum to drouſy Saints; Mr.</hi> Dyke <hi>of Conſcience, alſo of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; Dr.</hi> Preſtons <hi>of Gods all-ſufficiency;</hi> Watſons <hi>Cordial; Mr.</hi> Brooks <hi>of Jereboams ſon,</hi> for young men; <hi>Mr.</hi> Church <hi>Chriſtian daily Monitor.</hi> There are many other excellent works of Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Boulton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Preston,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sibbes, Mr.</hi> W. Fernner, <hi>Mr.</hi> Obadiah Sedgwick, <hi>Mr.</hi> Hooker, <hi>Dr.</hi> Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds, <hi>Mr.</hi> Burroughs, <hi>Mr.</hi> Caryl <hi>on Job, Dr.</hi> Goodwin, <hi>Mr.</hi> Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, <hi>Mr.</hi> Bridges, <hi>Mr.</hi> Swinnock, which I have ſeen, with very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, that come not now into my minde, and would be too too
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33936:32"/>tedious to write and read: but theſe few for direction to them that know not, and deſire ſome help herein.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Take and improve the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of hearing the word</hi> preached: eſpecially, on the Lords day, by able and ſound men in Office, (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have no warrant, nor call of God,) <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Be ſwift to hear. He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear,</hi> ſaid our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.15. and 13.41. For it is the onely ordinary means ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God, for to beget, and work, alſo to preſerve, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe ſaving knowledge, faith, repentance, and every ſaving grace. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 17. <hi>Faith comes by hearing,</hi> and that of men in Office, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>It is the power of God unto ſalvation.</hi> Rom. 1.16, 17. <hi>The ſavour of life unto life to them that do believe,</hi> 2 Cor. 2.16. Prov. 8.34. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that heareth me,</hi> (ſaith wiſdom) <hi>waiting daily at my gates, waiting at the poſts of my doors.</hi> He that willingly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects hearing, neglects his own ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33936:33"/>But be careful to hear with humble hearts, with much attention; to remember, believe, love, and practice what you hear: for, <hi>not the hearers, but the doers of the Law are bleſſed,</hi> Rom. 2.13. Jam. 1.22, 23, 25. And be earneſt with God in behalf of your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, that he may be a uſeful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of God to your ſoules; and eſteem him highly in love for the works ſake. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12, 13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Meditate often on the word</hi> you hear and read, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Meditate on theſe things; for bleſſed is the man that doth meditate therein day and night,</hi> Pſal. 1.1, 2. <hi>Oh how I love thy Law!</hi> ſaid <hi>David</hi> Pſal. 119.97. <hi>It is my meditation all the day.</hi> Meditate often, 1. Of your ſins, and what they deſerve. 2. Of your death. 3. Of the day of judgement. 4. Of the joys of Heaven. 5. Of the torments of Hell. And 6. Of God, eſpecially of the omniſcience, omnipreſence, power, juſtice and mercy, of God, and of the merit of Chriſt. Dr. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> has an excellent treatiſe of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33936:33"/>meditation, on <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. <hi>Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is of great uſe to further our knowledge and underſtanding in the things of God, to help our memories, ſtir up affections, help faith, repentance, love, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grace; put on to practice, and to bring in much ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and ſpiritual thought.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Be careful conſcientiouſly to keep the Chriſtian ſabbath, or Lords day holy:</hi> for we are expreſly ſo commanded, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.8. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Sabbath day, to keep it holy, viz.</hi> in all the duties of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, publick, private and ſecret: the whole day is the Lords, but for our ſpiritual advantage and benefit, who allows us ſix daies for our worldly buſineſs, reſerving only ſome ſmall portions of them, at our beſt advantage, to ſeek his bleſſing on our undertakings, and one whole day in ſeven for his ſervice, for us to exerciſe our ſelves in the works of piety and holyneſs, works of mercy and charity, and works of preſent and urgent neceſſity, that is, ſuch as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33936:34"/>could not be foreſeen and done before, nor cannot be put off to another day; as the feeding of the beaſts, watering them, quenching of fire broke out, helping a poor beaſt fallen into a ditch, and ſuch like. It is the Lords day, not ours, ſet apart not for our world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſs, actions, recreations, or diſcourſe, but his ſervice: God allows us ſix dayes for them, and this day, one in ſeven, and the firſt day of the week, for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as may be clearly concluded and proved from the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; Chriſts reſurrection, and reſting from the great work of our redemption; the practice of the Apoſtles, and the whole Church of God to this day. He that makes no conſcience of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lords day holy, will make as little conſcience of any other duty of piety towards God, or dealing with men.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Pray frequently, fervently, and conſtantly,</hi> in publick, in private, and in ſecret, alſo daily. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Pray without ceaſing,</hi> that is,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33936:34"/>daily, inſtantly, and conſtantly: not that we ſhould ſpend all our time in praying, and do nothing elſe; but keep a conſtant courſe of prayer, at the moſt convenient ſeaſons, daily, and be alſo ready to pray whenſoever there ſhall be a fit opportunity offered; have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a praying frame of heart, as much as may be. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.1. <hi>Our Saviour put forth a Parable,</hi> (ſayes the Evangeliſt) <hi>to this end, that men ſhould pray alwayes,</hi> that is, conſtantly, and importunately, <hi>and not faint.</hi> Eph. 6.18. <hi>Praying alwayes, i. e.</hi> on all ſeaſons, and fit opportunities, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pray at leaſt twice a day,</hi> morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening: the Jews had their morning and evening ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and incenſe offer'd, (a type of prayer.) <hi>Daniel,</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his great and weighty imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and publick buſineſs, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>three times a day ſolemnly on his knees,</hi> Dan. 6.10. David <hi>ſeven times a day,</hi> Pſal. 119.164. But many are like Heathens, and like the bruite beaſts, have no prayer in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33936:35"/>the Family, daily, or none in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; and ſome onely at night, in a ſhort, curtal, drowſy manner, without faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the morning</hi> when you wake, let your firſt ſerious thoughts be of God, and his goodneſs towards your ſelves and others the night paſt, and heartily praiſe God for them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.12. <hi>Praiſe thou the Lord O my ſoul, and all that is within me, praiſe his holy name. Bleſs the Lord O my ſoul, and forget not all his benefits, i.e.</hi> not any of them. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.1, 2. And when you are up and dreſſed, firſt addreſſe your ſelves to God, by humble and hearty praiſes, and prayer for grace, and power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin, and to live holily; for preſervation from evils, both of ſin and ſuffering; alſo for a bleſſing on your lawful undertakings, and thankfully acknowledge his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and benefits, and ſo labour to have your hearts filled with a ſenſe of Gods goodneſs, and holy reſolutions to walk with God as <hi>Enoch</hi> did.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:33936:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo at night,</hi> conſider what has been done that day paſt, and how: bleſs God for what hath been well done, for mercies received, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils prevented; his bleſſings on your undertakings, and aſſiſtance of you in your callings; humbly acknowledging and bewailing what has been done amiſs, beg pardon, and commit your ſelves and all to his protection and care, for the night, and time to come, in well doing.</p>
            <p>Uſe all kinds of prayer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, deprecation, petition, and thankſgiving.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Confeſſion:</hi> confeſs your ſins daily, humbly and unfeignedly to God, with ſorrow, and ſhame, and purpoſe of reforming what has been amiſs. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. <hi>He that covereth his ſins ſhall not proſper; but whoſo confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſins, ſhall have mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Deprecation:</hi> pray to God to remove evils felt, and prevent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils fear'd, both of affliction and trouble, but eſpecially the evil of ſin.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:33936:36"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Supplication, petition</hi> to God for mercy, pardon, power againſt ſin, and for good things needful both for ſoul and body, this life and that to come, for your ſelves and others, eſpecially for thoſe to whom you ſtand in a more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial relation: be earneſt with God for Magiſtrates, and for your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, as you love your own good and welfare of ſoul and body.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Thankſgiving,</hi> and praiſes: be thankful to God for every mercy and good thing privative and poſitive; for evils prevented, and removed, and for good things beſtowed and promiſed for ſoul and body, for your ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for this life and that to come, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 618. <hi>Praying alwayes with all prayer and ſupplication in the Spirit, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto with all perſeverance &amp; ſupplication for all Saints.</hi> 1 Tim. 2.1, 2. <hi>I exhort firſt of all, that ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks, be made for all men: for Kings, and all that are in Authority, that we may lead ae
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33936:36"/>quiet and peaceable life, in all God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Singing of Pſalms, Davids</hi> Pſalms eſpecially, and above all others, is an ancient, an heavenly, ſpiritual, comfortable, ſoul-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing Chriſtian duty; frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſed by the people of God, both under the old and new Teſtament, in the Church of God, above two thouſand (it may be three thouſand) years in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip of God; and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Families alſo, particularly, at the Paſſeover: the Jews uſed to ſing ſix Pſalms together, beginning at Pſalm 111 (ſome think Pſalm 112) and ſo on, as the Jewiſh Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, and other learned Divines do think, called <hi>the ſolemn Hymne,</hi> and <hi>the great Hallelujah.</hi> Further, how antient ſinging of Pſalms is, Read <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.1, 2, 4. and 92.1. and 147.1. How warrantable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the New Teſtament, See alſo, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.18, 19, 20. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.1.</p>
            <p>Which cuſtome 'tis probable our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33936:37"/>bleſſed Saviour obſerved, after the Paſſeover and his Supper were performed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. and his Diſciples. It was uſed even in mixt multitudes, and ſo comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Pſa</hi> 66.1, 2, 3, 4. &amp; 68.32. &amp; 96.1, 2. and 98.1, 2, 4, 5. Knowing what I do know, I wonder that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſober Chriſtians ſhould ſcruple at it, and lay it aſide: it was not wont to be ſo, till of late years the Enemie hath ſown his tares among the good Corn, thereby hoping to corrupt us with his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny foul errors, and ſo to divide and deſtroy us, and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion and Verity; which the God of truth forbid, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke the Enemie.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>In performing</hi> theſe and all other religious duties, <hi>have a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial care, and eye to the manner</hi> of doing them, as well as to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and duties themſelves; namely, to perform them</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Humbly</hi> and ſelf-denyingly, looking unto Chriſt both for aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and acceptance, without whom you can do nothing; ſo
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33936:37"/>himſelf ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 15.5. and we find it true by experience, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. that is, nothing rightly and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably by our own abilities, but only by the aſſiſtance and for the merit and interceſſion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Alſo do all duties with all the ſtrength of your intention and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.10. <hi>What thy hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might.</hi> Moſt neceſſary in performing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious duties, not coldly, careleſly, with wandring thoughts, or dead, drowſie affections, but with the heart kept cloſe to the duty, and with God in the duty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Alſo look to a right end:</hi> for the manner and end of doing du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, is that which God chiefly looks at, requires and accepts. <hi>Many by-reſpects</hi> and ends may put on to duties; but to do them in a right manner, and to a right end, principally to the Glory of God, and good of Souls, is that which is the heart, ſoul and life of a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, argues our faith in God, love to him, and obedience to his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33936:38"/>Authority, as moſt wiſe, juſt, and good: &amp; without this, the beſt duties are not regarded, but deſpiſed, rejected, and many times curſed and puniſhed; as the Jews ſervices and offerings, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.11, 12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>&amp; Iſa.</hi> 66.7. and <hi>Jehu</hi> his good works, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Obey Magiſtrates,</hi> them that have Authority over you, with all humility &amp; cheerfulneſs; obſerving their commands for conſcience ſake, for ſo we are commanded, and Nature teacheth us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. <hi>For they are the Miniſters of God: the Powers that are, are ordained of God.</hi> And yet the Rulers that then were in being were wicked men, Tyrants and Heathens, whom the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, Jer.</hi> 29.7. and the Apoſtles commanded to pray for; as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Nero,</hi> and thoſe under them: much more ought we to pray for, and obey Chriſtian Magiſtrates. And in caſe any thing ſhould be commanded (which God forbid, I ſpeak by way of ſuppoſition) which upon
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33936:38"/>ſerious conſideration you cannot be perſwaded can ſtand with your obedience to God the Supreme Lord, &amp; the peace of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, forbear to act, yet with all humble reſpect to Authority, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting willingly to ſuffer, rather than to ſin; as the three Noble men did <hi>Dan</hi> 3.16, 17, 18. and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, chapt.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 10, 11. and the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.19. In all other things obey the Magiſtrate Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme and Sub-ordinate, readily and chearfully, and thereby give good proof of your Loyalty, and that you are not ſtubborn and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory; ſo that if any ſhould ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly ſlander you, or falſely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe you, you may ſay as <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 24.13. <hi>They cannot prove the things whereof they now accuſe me:</hi> and as <hi>Daniel, Innocencie is found before me, and alſo before thee, O King, have I done no burt,</hi> Dan. 6.22. and as it is <hi>Act.</hi> 24.16. <hi>I do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe my ſelf to have always a good conſcience void of offence towards God and towards men;</hi> and as it is 2 <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1.12. <hi>Our rejoycing is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33936:39"/>this, the teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, we have had our converſation in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo pray heartily &amp; daily for the King,</hi> and all in Authority under him, that under them ye may live a quiet and peaceable life, in all Godlineſs and honeſty; for ſo we are commanded as a thing well-pleaſing unto God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>That ſo doing, ye may put to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence the ignorance and malice of fooliſh men,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.15. eſpecially Popiſh perſons, who are ready to ſay they are enemies to Kings, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and Government; ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, diſobedient, and ſelf-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, rebels to Authority; the great and common Argument ſome men uſe againſt thoſe that are moſt qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, conſcientious, and do moſt heartily pray for Kings and all in Authority, deſiring their good every way, and the publike wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and proſperity, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3 4.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Have a lawful calling,</hi> and uſe it lawfully. Have a lawful calling, ſome honeſt imployment, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33936:39"/>ſuch as will conduce to the publike good, as well as to your own particular benefit; ſuch a calling as is of good report, and ſutable to your means, parts, abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and condition. This I ſpeak to them that are yet to chuſe a calling; yet ſuch imployments as are ſinful (ſo ſome are) ought to be caſt off. And in a lawful cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling be faithful, careful, juſt, and diligent in it, avoyding idleneſs, waſtfulneſs and covetouſneſs. This duty God laid on man in the ſtate of innocencie, to keep him honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imployed, and his mind buſied; but after the fall, toylſome labour came in as a puniſhment for ſin. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.17, 18, 19. <hi>In the ſweat of thy face, thou ſhalt eat thy bread, till thou return unto the ground.</hi> Exod. 20.9. <hi>Six days thou ſhalt labour:</hi> God allows no perſon whatſoever to live without a lawful cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and imployment, that is capable of doing ſomething. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſs was one of the ſins of <hi>Sodom.</hi> An idle perſon <hi>est pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinar diaboli,</hi> the Devils cuſhion,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33936:40"/>on which he delights to ſit; and his anvil on which he uſes to ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer miſchief. Of ſuch an active nature are our ſpirits, that if we do not buſie them about that which is good, the devil will be ſure to ſet them about that which is evil. You read what ſad temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations befel <hi>David</hi> when he was idle; and what ſad doings follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but it coſt him very dear, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12 9 &amp;c. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>Deal justly and faithfully</hi> with all men, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they obſerve you or not. God ſeeth and abhorreth all unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, lying, diſſembling, coze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and defrauding, even the moſt ſimple and ignorant. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Let no man go beyond or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud his Brother in any matter, for the Lord is an avenger of all ſuch.</hi> It is an excellent rule which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour gives, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.31. <hi>As ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye alſo to them likewiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore having a lawful cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and imployment, labour to manage it lawfully, wiſely, and Chriſtianly.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:33936:40"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Wiſely;</hi> watch to obſerve and improve the ſeaſons and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities God offers for the managing your callings and affairs for the beſt advantage to your ſelves and others, in an honeſt way, without covetouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Chriſtianly:</hi> manage your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings Chriſtianly and Religiouſly; that is, with a right Principle, in a right manner, and to a right end.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Manage your calling and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs <hi>with a right principle,</hi> namely by doing lawful and good things: 1. <hi>In faith,</hi> praying for aſſiſtance in your undertakings, and for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of your endeavours, and a bleſſing from God on your law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful endeavours, <hi>for without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14 23. 2. <hi>Out of love and obedience</hi> to God, who will have all perſons to be buſied in ſome honeſt imployment, that they may be the better able to live comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably themſelves, and be the more helpful to others, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. to manage and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what they have. No man is born for himſelf only.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:33936:41"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe your calling</hi> as much as may be in <hi>an holy, Chriſtian and heavenly manner;</hi> not with earthly, carnal, ſenſual affections, greedily coveting and carking cares, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, delighting, and ſolacing your ſelves inordinately in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward good things, as if they were the only or chief good.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>To a right end:</hi> Do all you do to this end, chiefly that God may have the Glory of his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Authority, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs in appointing you ſuch a calling to be employ'd in, giving ability to manage it, and a bleſſing on honeſt endeavors. See <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17. <hi>That God may be therefore glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by your ſelves and others.</hi> Mat. 5.16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in Heaven:</hi> Not only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious works, but civil actions al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and natural, as eating, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſleeping, and the reſt: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 31. <hi>Whether ye eat or drink, or whatſoever ye do, do all to the glory of God.</hi> So <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thus labour to make Religion
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33936:41"/>your chief buſineſs;</hi> that is, ſeriouſly and induſtriouſly endeavour to be Religious, Chriſtians in all your ways, and at all times. Let it not be your <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not a work by the by, at ſome leiſure time, when nothing elſe to do; but the principal work, to which all others ſhould be ſubſervient; your worldly imployments, jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyings, eating, drinking, ſleeping, viſiting, entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of friends, recreations, as well as actions of Religion, as reading, hearing, praying, meditation, ſinging, receiving the Sacrament, and all your thoughts, diſcourſes, words and deeds, be directed, moulded, limited, and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated by Religion, the word of God, the Doctrine which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Godlineſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.7. for this is the great end for which we were made, and came into the world; and this will be our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt honour and happineſs, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hereafter in Heaven, but even in this life, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11, 12.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:33936:42"/>
            <p>
               <hi>This is the way to be every way bleſſed,</hi> and in every condition, and to make your civil calling and worldly imployments, and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral actions alſo, to be ſo many ſteps toward Heaven and eternal life, as God no doubt intended we ſhould do, when he appointed ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil callings and worldly imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for men.</p>
            <p>It is a great honour, ornament, and ennobling to a man, to a Chriſtian, to be Godly and holy in all relations and imployments; yea, it doth more honour and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble a man, than any worldly greatneſs, of birth, eſtate, wealth, or place of worldly honour can do; as the renowned Emperor <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and alſo a Noble Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaid, and the Holy Ghoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo witneſſeth, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Be watchful for the good of your bodies,</hi> but eſpecially for the good of your Souls, both to do and receive good, and avoid evil.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be watchful to obſerve and improve the ſeaſons and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33936:42"/>for the doing of good to your ſelves and to others, both for Souls and bodies. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>As we have opportunity, let us do good unto all men, eſpecially to them which are of the houſhold of faith; i. e.</hi> that are of the ſame Church, faith, and profeſſion of Religion; by praying for them, inſtructing, counſelling, admoniſhing, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, exhortation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; relieving them in any ſtrait or trouble, according as we have opportunity and ability.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be watchful to obſerve and improve the opportunities and ſeaſons of <hi>receiving</hi> and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting good; as of reading, praying, hearing, meditation, receiving, Chriſtian diſcourſe, and the like. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.15. <hi>See that ye walk cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly, not as fools, but as wiſe; redeeming the time, becauſe the days are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Watch diligently againſt evil, to avoid and prevent it, both evil of ſin and of ſuffering, as much as lawfully you may. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.3. <hi>The prudent man foreſeeth the evil,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33936:43"/>and hideth himſelf; but the ſimple paſs on and are puniſhed.</hi> Which watchfulneſs conſiſteth in four things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In a due trial and examining your words and actions, eſpecially ſuch as are doubtful and queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, whether they be lawful or no, before you do them. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Ponder the path of thy feet, and let all thy ways be eſtabliſhed:</hi> or thus, <hi>So ſhall all thy ways be eſtabliſhed;</hi> that is, rightly ordered. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>The wiſemans eyes are in his head,</hi> that is, to foreſee at a diſtance, and to order things aright: and if they be lawful, then to conſider whether they be expedient at this time, in this place, company, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the like; otherwiſe we may raſhly run into great evils or inconveniences when we think we do well.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obſerve well the corruptions of your natures, eſpecially your ſpecial corruptions, boſome-luſts; for though in all men are all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſinful luſts, at leaſt habitual, that is, the habits of all evil luſts;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33936:43"/>yet every man hath ſome ſpecial &amp; maſter-ſins which do moſt aſſault, &amp; moſt eaſily deceive us, which we are moſt ready to hearken to: as all the four humors are mixt in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans body, but ſome one in every man is more predominant than the others; warch againſt theſe, (which luſts <hi>David</hi> called <hi>His iniquity,</hi> Pſal. 18.23.) Thoſe eſpecially; labour alſo to ſubdue and mortifie them.</p>
            <p>Alſo obſerve well the ſins that do uſually accompany your parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular callings, relations, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, the times in which ye live, and the places where you live; and watch diligently againſt them, to avoid them, out of obedience to God, and becauſe ſins.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Avoid carefully all occaſions of evil, as evil company, times and places, as much as you can. He that will voluntarily venture on occaſions, ſhall oftentimes fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſins alſo, which he ſhould not, (and 'tis like would not) to his ſhame and ſorrow, when too late to repent them; therefore
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33936:44"/>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22. ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from all appearances of evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And where occaſions cannot be avoided, there eſpecially arm your ſelves by prayer, meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the word, power, juſtice and goodneſs of God, and by holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, conſtantly and reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to oppoſe the evil, the motions of ſin, temptations of Satan, and the allurements of the world; looking unto God, and relying on him for aſſiſtance, ſtrength and wiſdom to withſtand and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4 7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41. <hi>Watch and pray always, that ye enter not into temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we have great reaſon ſo to do, to be watchful, if we conſider what enemies we have, <hi>viz.</hi> the Devil, the world, and the fleſh.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Devil,</hi> a moſt cunning, malicious, ſubtil, vigilant, and diligent (and deceitful) adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to tempt and draw us to ſin and deſtruction: See 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. one that is inviſible, a ſpirit, and ſo can be preſent, and ſee us out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly &amp; inwardly, &amp; that knows
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33936:44"/>our nature, temper, and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by his great knowledge, and thouſands of years diligent obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and can and doth ſute his temptations accordingly, and preſs them home again and often, and not be ſeen nor diſcerned of us, becauſe a ſpirit and inviſible.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The World,</hi> another great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy; both the men of the world, and worldly things. The men of the world, earthly, carnal, ſenſual men, and men of corrupt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and evil converſations, that will be tempting and drawing to ſin by their counſel, promiſes, threatnings, fair and foul uſage, hard dealings, by their examples, habits, carriage, and the like. Therefore there are ſo many warnings given us by the Lord in his word: as <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.10. <hi>My ſon, if ſinners intice thee, conſent thou not.</hi> Prov. 4.14. <hi>Enter not into the path of the wicked, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 10.16, 17, 18. <hi>Beware of men.</hi> Mat. 7.15. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of falſe Prophets that come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in ſheeps clothing, but inwardly are ravening wolves;</hi> i. e. with fair
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33936:45"/>pretences, but with foul malicious devouring hearts, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. <hi>Evil words corrupt good manners.</hi> 2 Tim. 2.17. <hi>Their words do eat as doth a canker.</hi> One man is oftentimes a wolf, a devil to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and yet many diſcern it not.</p>
            <p>Alſo the things of the world, as profit, pleaſure, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, eaſe, liberty, credit, and the like, are great ſnares many times to draw into ſin. Who is not many times enſnared by them, or too much taken up with them? therefore great cauſe we have to be watchful.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The fleſh</hi> within us, is as bad an enemy or worſe than either of the other, becauſe within us, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to us, born and bred up al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes up with us; as near to us as a right hand, or a right eye, that is always preſent with us, and ready to open to Satan, who is not always preſent; therefore be watchful.</p>
            <p>And thus labour <hi>to walk circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, exactly, preciſely, (for ſo the word moſt properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies)
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33936:45"/>
               <hi>not as fools but as wiſe, redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time, becauſe the days are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> Epheſ. 5.15, 16. from plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, recreations, idle words, and frivolous diſcourſes, which are apt to ſteal away and ſwallow up much time, though not evil in themſelves; alſo from vain thoughts, and unprofitable mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which are very apt to ſteal in upon us in the bed at night, in the morning, and at other times, at home and abroad, walking and journeying; alſo from ſight, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and amorous Books, Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the like, very unfit for Chriſtians profeſſing Godlineſs to read, or hear, for they ſteal much precious time, move the affections in vain, corrupt youth, and take their affections off from, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reliſh the ſpiritual appetite to the Holy Scriptures, and other divine Treatiſes very neceſſary to be read frequently, and ſeriouſly thought of. Alſo redeem the time from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary journeys, viſits; yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from ſleep and worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, for ſpiritual exerciſes, to get
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33936:46"/>and grow in knowledge, grace and holineſs, to make ſure of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, pardon of ſin, intereſt in Chriſt, and eternal life; and to be uſeful in your generation, &amp; that you may be able to to ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Our converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in Heaven, from whence we look for the Saviour the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who ſhall change our vile bodies.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="11">11. As God gives, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your abilities, be ready to be good to, and relieve them that are ſick, weak, in want, or other affliction, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>As we have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, let us do good to all men, eſpecially unto them that are of the houſhold of faith,</hi> i. e. that are of the ſame Religion with us, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuch as are Godly. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16. <hi>To do good, and to communicate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not; for with ſuch ſacrifice God is well pleaſed. It is an odour of a ſweet ſavour, a ſacrifice acceptable, &amp; well-pleaſing to God,</hi> Phil. 4.18. And do it chearfully and liberally, not grudgingly and ſparingly, <hi>for God loveth a cheerful giver,</hi> and will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33936:46"/>plentifully require them in <hi>full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, preſſed down and running over,</hi> Luk. 6.38. It is compared to a ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſeed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. <hi>He that ſows ſparingly, ſhall reap ſparingly; and he that ſoweth bountifully, ſhall reap boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully.</hi> Liberality ſupplieth the want of the neceſſitous, giving occaſion of much thankſgiving, and of glory to God, doth adorn the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, honor the Goſpel of Chriſt, ſtop the mouths of worldly men, but opens the mouths and hearts of them that are relieved, refreſhed, and comforted, to praiſe God for you, ſpeak wel of you, pray to God for you; and doth (as I may in ſome ſenſe ſay) engage God to deal liberally with you, for your liberal diſtribution to others; (though our good works do not merit in the leaſt degree) and to inrich you with every good thing to all bountifulneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7, 8. <hi>and</hi> 9.8. <hi>to the end.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten preſſeth this duty: Read <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.1, 2. <hi>Cast thy bread upon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> (though it ſeem in the eye of natural reaſon, as bread caſt into the River, quite loſt) <hi>yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>after
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33936:47"/>many days thou ſhalt find it again;</hi> yea, with much advantage: as the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man doth his corn, caſt into the earth and long buried, yet after many moneths he receives it again many for one, many times ten, twelve, yea, more for one buſhel. <hi>Ver.</hi> 2. <hi>Give a portion to ſeven, and alſo to eight, for thou knoweſt not what evil ſhall be on the earth;</hi> that is, what plundering times, or caſualties may come, when all may be taken away, or conſumed; and then it will not repent you that you were liberal and charitable whilſt you had it, to poor Chriſtians and other prous uſes: that is ſo given, is ſure and ſafe; but that which is not given, but taken away or conſumed, is quite gone &amp; loſt, unleſs loſt for Chriſts ſake. But remember as to give cheerfully and liberally, to alſo for Chriſts ſake, love to God, and obedience to his command, and brotherly compaſſion to the poor, with an humble heart, looking to God only for a reward of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, according to his gratious and free promiſe, <hi>Luk</hi> 6.38 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>to the end:</hi> alſo 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17, 18, 19.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33936:47"/>Remember <hi>the poor widow</hi> that gave two mites, all that ſhe had by her, and was highly commended for it by the Lord himſelf, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.42, 43, 44. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.42.43.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>In proſperity,</hi> as in health, ſtrength, eaſe, peace, liberty, plenty, courteous reſpects from others, good ſucceſs in lawful undertakings, and the like.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Labour to ſee the good hand of God in all outward good things; for, <hi>God is the God of all mercies,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.3. <hi>Every good gift is from above, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down from the Father of Lights,</hi> Jam. 1.17. 1 Chron. 29.11, 12. <hi>It is God that giveth power to get wealth;</hi> Deut. 8.18. even when men are moſt induſtrious and inſtrumental. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion cometh neither from the East nor from the West, but God putteth down one, and ſetteth up another,</hi> Pſal. 75.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thankfully acknowledge Gods goodneſs in every thing, and give him the praiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Uſe all his benefits in thoſe ways and to thoſe ends and uſes to which God hath appointed, and ſerve him more cheerfully with them
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33936:48"/>and for them. It is a great abuſe of Gods benefits, and diſhonour to God, to hoard them up covetouſly to look on, or delight in exceſs of eating, drinking, apparel, laviſh, idle expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, gaming, to bribe ſome, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs others, or to be proud of them, and Lord it over others, or to ſlight and neglect them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In abundance labour to keep thy heart humble, and be courteous towards all, even to the meaneſt. Take heed of being proud, or domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering over the poor, or ſlighting them, as rich men are apt to do; for who made thee to differ from the meaneſt and pooreſt?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Even in abundance take heed of truſting in any worldly things, but labour to live in the world above the world, truſting and relying on God alone, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.10. <hi>If riches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, ſet not your hearts upon them.</hi> 1 Tim. 6.17, 18. Take heed of being enſnared by them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Uſe the world with weaned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Sit looſe to all worldly things, as friends, children, worldly
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33936:48"/>goods, that you may be ready to part with them whenſoever, or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God ſhall pleaſe to take them from you, or you from them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29, 30, 31. If outward things ſtick to us, or we to them, as our skin on our back, as a right hand, or right eye, they will very hardly be parted with; but if they fit looſe in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, as a looſe garment on us, or as a wooden legg, or arm, or glaſs-eye, then it will be eaſie to part with them. To this end conſider how vain, empty, uncertain, and unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying all worldly things are, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to give us any true comfort, peace, eaſe of Conſcience, or of outward pain many times, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Gods favour, pardon of ſin, freedom from wrath, and the like; alſo how many cares and troubles do uſually accompany worldly eſtates: conſider <hi>Judas</hi> his caſe, his money then would not comfort him; and <hi>Hamans, Esth.</hi> 5.9, 11, 12, 13, <hi>and</hi> 7.7, 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>In adverſity, viz.</hi> in ſickneſs, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, pain, reproaches, poverty, in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, loſſes, croſſes, and the like.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33936:49"/>
            <p n="1">1. Labour to ſee Gods hand in all theſe things; for God hath a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, wiſe, and gratious providence in all theſe things, and for good to all his: <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. <hi>Is there any evil in the City</hi> (namely of puniſhment or ſuffering) <hi>and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> Iſa. 45.7. <hi>I form the light and create darkneſs, I make peace and create evil, I the Lord do all theſe things. Afflictions come not out of the duſt,</hi> Job 5.6. Therefore own, acknowledge, and juſtifie God in all his dealings, though never ſo ſharp and grievous to fleſh and blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Labour, if it may be, to find out the particular cauſe, the ſin that is the cauſe of your ſuffering; ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly confeſs your ſins, bewail them, and reſolve to amend what is amiſs. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30, 31. <hi>If we would judge our ſelves, we ſhould not be condemned with the world,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Be patient, humble, and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit to the good pleaſure of God. Be willing to be what God would have you to be; he knows beſt what is fitteſt for us: take heed of murmuring, repining, fretting at
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33936:49"/>his hand, diſtruſting God; much more of uſing any unlawful, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable means to be freed. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, take heed of ſeeking unto cunning men or women for help or eaſe; that is, in plain terms, to go to the devil for help, when God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts, (a hainous crime:) for what, or whoſoever is the inſtrument, yet God is the Author of afflictions and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; therefore <hi>Job,</hi> though his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings were exceeding great from the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> the <hi>Sabeans,</hi> and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil that ſet them all on, did not ſay, the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> or <hi>Sabeans,</hi> or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; but, <hi>the Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken, and bleſſed be the Name of the Lord</hi> he looked at Gods hand in all, and juſtified God.</p>
            <p>God lays afflictions on his people, either to correct them for ſin, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and bring them home to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; or to exerciſe, and diſcover the truth and ſtrength of their faith and other graces, as patience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to brighten them, and make them more illuſtrious. Alſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that out greateſt and ſharpeſt ſufferings are much leſs than we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33936:50"/>and we ſuffer moſt juſtly, but Jeſus Chriſt moſt unjuſtly, and yet bore it moſt patiently.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Look on the Examples of the Godly, and how patiently they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. <hi>and Heb. Chap.</hi> 11. eſpecially <hi>ver.</hi> 37. <hi>to the end. Jam.</hi> 5.7, 8, 9, 10. yea, the Lord Chriſt himſelf, though moſt innocent, and made it his whole work to go about to do good, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>and</hi> 4.12, 13, 14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conſider how many good things you have, which many others want; be thankful and contented: conſider alſo that many others ſuffer as well as you, yea, in the ſame kind; and others in ſome kind or other, as much, as large, and ſome much more grievouſly, even ſuch as are dear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, as <hi>Job, David, Paul,</hi> and many others, even unto the death.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Conſider alſo the many promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes God hath made.</p>
            <p>As 1. That he will lay no more on his Servants than they ſhall be able to bear. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. And if he lay on more burden, he will give them more ſtrength, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4, 5. And ſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33936:50"/>a very great burden or ſuffering will be no more troubleſome than a ſmall matter with little ſtrength.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he will be preſent with you in afflictions and troubles: Read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41 12, 13. <hi>and</hi> 43.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all afflictions and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing croſs-Providences are out of his love, in mercy and faithfulneſs, for their good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That he will deliver his out of all troubles and ſufferings, make a way for them to eſcape in the beſt time, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That he will abundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and crown all their patient, humble ſuffering in a quiet ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to his will. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10, 12, 26. for his ſake, and well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11, 12, 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17, 18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18.</p>
            <p>Further, God in afflictions and ſuffering very often helps the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his ſervants, to call to mind theſe and ſuch like gratious ſutable promiſes, and helps their faith to believe them, and reſt on them for aſſiſtance, the comfort and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of them in his beſt time:
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33936:51"/>for, <hi>all the promiſes in Chriſt are Yea and Amen;</hi> ſure and certain, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. by which they are inabled to overcome all ſufferings and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to triumph in the end; 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4. Conſider therefore the patience of <hi>Job,</hi> and what end the Lord made of it, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>and</hi> 5.11. alſo of <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſufferings, and the happy iſſue; the great prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and honour that followed, and the very great good he was inabled to do, not only to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> but to the Church of God. <hi>Gen. chapt.</hi> 41.45. <hi>and</hi> 50. <hi>For the Lord is very pitiful, and of tender mercy,</hi> Jam. 5.11.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Be ſure to endeavour truly to repent, to believe in Jeſus Chriſt, to walk holily, and to make your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and election ſure, that you are in the favour of God, and that he afflicts in mercy, out of love, and with faithfulneſs, for our eternal good, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>In Temptations to ſin,</hi> conſider theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be not ſelf-confident, go not out in your own ſtrength, be always jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33936:51"/>and ſuſpitious of your ſelves, and look unto God for wiſdom, to ſee the evil in them, &amp; for grace and power to withſtand and overcome them. Remember <hi>Peter,</hi> a good ſoul, but relying too much on his own ſtrength, was ſham fully foiled, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.33, 71, 72, 73 74.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Arm your ſerves in the beſt wiſe ye can: 1. by prayer: 2. with ſome good Scriptures, as ſutable as you can find to your occaſion, and preſent temptation; the word is, <hi>The ſword of the Spirit,</hi> Epheſ. 6.17. 3. <hi>The ſhield of faith, whereby you will be able to quench all the fiery darts of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> ver. 16. and 4. Confider and reſt your ſelves on the promiſes, the power, goodneſs, and faithfulneſs of God: and 5. with an holy reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to ſuffer any thing rather than to ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider what a ſhameful and diſhonorable a thing it is to yeeld to Satan, and be overcome of ſin and Satan; and the ſad conſequents u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fually follow: and then conſider al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the comfort, peace, and honour of not yeelding, but overcoming, with
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33936:52"/>the encouraging promiſes made to them that do overcome, and hold out in well-doing to the end, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17, 26. <hi>But reſist him ſtedfaſtly in the faith,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.9. that is, by laying hold on 1. the faithfulneſs of God, believing the promiſes as moſt true, the threatnings alſo, the precepts as holy, juſt, and good. 2. By laying hold on the power, mercy, wiſdome, and goodneſs of God. Faith reaſons thus, the <hi>Promiſes</hi> are true and ſure, why ſhould I nor believe them, and reſt upon them? The <hi>Threatnings</hi> are ſure, why ſhould I then venture on ſin? the <hi>Precepts</hi> are all holy, juſt &amp; good, therefore all reaſon I ſhould obſerve &amp; keep them. God hath been loving, good, and merciful to me, therefore I would not offend him; and he is able, all ſufficient to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, ſtrengthen me in, and deliver me out of all in due time; therefore I will reſt upon him alone.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As God gives in wiſdom to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the evil in temptations, and ability and ſtrength of Grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and overcome them; ſo give to God all the praiſe and glory, he is
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33936:52"/>moſt worthy of it. Thankfulneſs for benefits received, is (as I may ſay) an holy inducement to move God to do more, who delights to do good to thankful Souls.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Study unity, peace, and love towards one another, and towards all men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Study unity both in judgment and affection. As much as poſſibly may be, labour to be all of one judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and one mind in the Lord; and where you cannot be all of one judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet labour to be all of one heart, to love all that are ſound in their judgments in all truths neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to life and godlineſs, and joyn with them in all Ordinances of Chriſt. How can I ſeparate from them whom Chriſt owns and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives? and where any do differ only in circumſtantials, or leſſer matters, that may ſtand with God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, bear with them, pity them, cover their weakneſſes in love, and uſe all loving means to inform them a right, and gain them to the truth. <hi>Beware of cenſuring others</hi> that are not of the ſame judgment and way with
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33936:53"/>your ſelves in thoſe ſmaller matters, being otherwiſe found, holding the foundation, and blameleſs in their lives, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.2. God doth not give alike knowledge and underſtanding to every one. And <hi>eſpecially</hi> beware of diviſion and ſeparation from any whom Chriſt owns and receives. The <hi>cenſoriouſneſs,</hi> diviſion, and ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Profeſſors, hath almoſt undone us; weakned the Proteſtants very much, given a great wound to the Proteſtant Religion, brought a great ſcandal upon Profeſſors, Religion, and Godlineſs; given occaſion to many looſe Proteſtants to ſlight all Religion, many to turn Atheiſts, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers prophane, and given the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Adverſary very great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by our diviſions, to deſtroy both the Proteſtant Religion, and the Profeſſors of it. You know that a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of ſticks or arrows taken ſingly one after another may all eaſily be broken, but joyntly bound together they cannot. Therefore the Romiſh Adverſaries have of late years en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavored, and do ſtill endeavour what in them lieth to ſow errors, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33936:53"/>others, and make diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Proteſtants, that they may deſtroy them, and the Truth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; and ſet up their Romiſh Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian idolatrous Maſſes and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But let not any of you (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, and I hope in the Lord you will never be) the Jeſuites and Devils inſtruments to make diviſions, rents, and ſeparation in the Church of Chriſt, which is a work of the fleſh, and forbidden of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. <hi>and</hi> 1.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.</p>
            <p>The Lord doth often and much command and preſs to unity. Read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1, 2, <hi>to</hi> 8. <hi>If there be therefore any conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind. Let nothing be done through ſtrife or vain glory, but in lowlineſs of mind, let each eſteem others better than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</hi> and ſo on. Epheſ. 4.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Endeavour to keep the unity of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the bond of peace.</hi> Obſerve his weighty Reaſons: 1. <hi>There is one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:33936:54"/>namely myſtical, the Church of Chriſt. 2. <hi>One Spirit,</hi> by whom they are united and governed. 3. <hi>Ye are called into one hope,</hi> to wit, of life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. 4. <hi>Have the ſame Lord,</hi> even Chriſt. 5. <hi>Have one faith,</hi> namely, in Chriſt. 6. <hi>Have the ſame Baptiſm,</hi> to wit, into the Name of Chriſt, or bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity. 7. and have <hi>one God and Father.</hi> Rom. 16.17. <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren, mark them which cauſe diviſions among you, and avoid them.</hi> He that ſeparateth from a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, a child of God, or any one whom Chriſt ewneth and receiveth, though never ſo weak and mean, doth ſo far ſeparate and diſown Chriſt himſelf, who is the Head of that Member. Conſider <hi>Titus</hi> 3.2. <hi>Speak evil of no man:</hi> alſo <hi>Jude ver.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Endeavour what in you lieth the peace</hi> of the Church and Common-wealth. <hi>Mark</hi> 9.50. <hi>Have peace one with another.</hi> Rom. 14.19. <hi>Follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the things which make for peace, and wherein one may edifie another.</hi> Heb. 12.14. <hi>Follow after peace and holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee God.</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:33936:54"/>2 Cor. 13.11. <hi>Finally, Brethren, be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Goſpel is the <hi>Goſpel of peace,</hi> Rom. 10.15. Peace is <hi>the frequent wiſh and prayer</hi> of the Apoſtle in every E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle; <hi>one end of our calling,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.15. God is <hi>the God of peace,</hi> Rom. 15.33. <hi>Chriſt is the Prince of Peace,</hi> Epheſ. 2.14. <hi>Our peace, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker,</hi> Col. 1.10. It is <hi>one of the laſt Legacies</hi> Chriſt gave to his Church, <hi>John</hi> 14.27. <hi>A fruit of the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 5.22. Therefore <hi>let the peace of God rule in your hearts,</hi> Col. 3.15. For <hi>bleſſed are the peace-makers,</hi> Mat. 5.9. Labour therefore for a peaceable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, avoid contentions, <hi>ſtudy to be quiet, and mind your own buſineſs,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.11. Many and great are the benefits of peace, but woful are the fruits of contentions and diviſions, eſpecially of War.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Alſo love one another;</hi> yea, all men; godly perſons for Godlineſs ſake; civil and moral men, for their civility and morality, temperance, juſtice, truth, civilities, and the like. Yea, alſo evil men and enemies, love
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33936:55"/>their perſons, pity them, pray for them, exerciſe civility and Chriſtian carriage towards them, but ſhun their evil courſes and wicked opinions and ways, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Love as Brethren, be pitiful, be courteous,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.22. <hi>See that ye love one another, with a pure heart fervently.</hi> It is Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. <hi>Love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, pray for them that deſpitefully uſe you, and perſecute you, and do good to them that hate you, that you may be the children of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven, for he maketh his Sun to ſhine on the good and on the bad, &amp;c.</hi> 1 John 4.7, 8. <hi>Beloved, let us love one another; every one that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth,</hi> i. e. truly, heartily, for God's and Chriſts ſake, <hi>is born of God. He that loveth not, knoweth not God.</hi> 1 Joh. 3.14, 15. <hi>We know that we are paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the Brethren. He that hateth his brother a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth in death: whoſoever hateth his brother is a murderer, and you know that no murtherer hath eternal life abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in him.</hi> See before.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Endeavour to be, and alwayes walk in the fear of the Lord:</hi> I mean,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33936:55"/>an holy fear of offending God, any way, out of love to God. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.17. <hi>Be thou in the fear of the Lord all the day long, for happy is he that feareth always,</hi> Prov. 28 14. <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdom.</hi> Prov. 1.7. <hi>and</hi> 9.10. <hi>A good underſtanding have all they that do thereafter.</hi> Pſalm 111.10. <hi>The fear of the Lord is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from evil,</hi> Prov. 3.7. and 8.13. and 16.6. <hi>It prolongeth life.</hi> Pro. 19.27. <hi>Tendeth to life.</hi> Prov. 19.23. <hi>And a little with the fear of the Lord, is better than great treaſure without it.</hi> Conſider, I pray, that you are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in his preſence, and that he takes notice of all your deeds, words and thoughts, and that we muſt give an account of our ſelves, and all our ways unto God. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13, 14. <hi>Fear God and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole duty of man. For God will bring every work into judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> &amp;c. So 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10. And therefore as much as in you li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, endeavour to live every day as if it were the laſt.</p>
            <p>To this end mind two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, be careful to avoid and ſhun
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33936:56"/>all evil, and occaſions of ſin.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All ſin as much as may be, in deed, word, or thought. <hi>Sin is the tranſgreſſion of the Law of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4. any ſwerving from the Law of God in the matter, manner, order, time, meaſure, or end. And ſin, and nothing but ſin, is evil in it ſelf, or own nature, forbidden of God, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of him, and ſeverely puniſhed by him; is filthy, defiles the Soul; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and damnable, the only me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious cauſe of all evil of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſorrow whatſoever, in body, eſtate, name, liberty, Soul, mind, here; and both in Soul and body hereafter for ever in Hell. Therefore be always afraid of ſinning againſt God, out of love of God and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which are ſo tranſcendently good; and out of hatred of ſin, that is ſo exceedingly evil, and will bring nothing but ſhame and ſorrow, moſt intolerable miſery for ever. How pleaſing ſoever ſin ſeems to ſinners now, it will be extreme bitter in the end. And eſpecially</p>
            <p n="2">2. Shun all occaſions of ſin.</p>
            <p>As firſt, <hi>Evil company;</hi> there is a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33936:56"/>great danger of being enſnared and brought into ſin by evil company, at leaſt of being grieved by them; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>Dinahs</hi> caſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.1, 2. Alſo <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.9, 10, <hi>&amp;c. Prov.</hi> 13.2. <hi>He that walketh with wiſe men ſhall be wiſe; but a companion of fools ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Obſerve, not the fool only, but he alſo that accompanies with him: therefore ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 4.14, 15. <hi>Enter not into the path of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, avoid it, paſs by it, turn away from it.</hi> Very many hopeful perſons have been utterly undone every way, in their name, eſtates, bodies and ſouls, by evil companions. In any compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where you have not a neceſſary obligation to be with them, where you have no hope of doing good, nor receiving good, ſo ſoon as with civility you may, leave them. <hi>Pro.</hi> 5.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.22, 23, 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13. <hi>and</hi> 15 33 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>And eſpecially take heed of being tainted with the foul errors, corrupt opinions, and the ſins and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the times wherein you live. The fuller the world is of defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the greater muſt your care be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33936:57"/>to keep your ſelves unſpotted of the world, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. As <hi>Noah</hi> kept himſelf clear from the corruptions of the old World; <hi>Lot</hi> preſerved himſelf pure from the pollutions of <hi>Sodom; Daniel</hi> was not defiled with the ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Thus the fiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains his freſhneſs in the ſalt Sea; the roſe its ſweetneſs amongſt the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome weeds; and the Diamond its brightneſs though it lie in the duſt. Keep your ſelves pure from foul er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and ſins, as you would have God preſerve you ſafe in dangerous times, as he did <hi>Noah</hi> in the Ark, <hi>Daniel</hi> and the three Nobles in <hi>Babylon, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiels</hi> mourners, <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, avoid evil places, places of evil reſort, and of evil report, for uncleanneſs, drinking, gaming, or any other vice or ungodlineſs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Avoid alſo all evil times: ſome times and ſeaſons, as well as ſome places, are evil &amp; dangerous to walk in, eſpecially at ſome places; as the night late, or very early in ſome places. Every man by nature is
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33936:57"/>like to dry wood; yea, to dried tinder, which is apt to take fire ſo ſoon as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpark of temptation to ſin is caſt into us by Satan: and if the Devil do not tempt us, yet our corrupt hearts are apt to take fire as ſoon as the leaſt occaſion is offered to us, or we meet with it, as too frequent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience proves. Yea,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Labour to mortifie ſin, every inordinate luſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie your members which are upon the earth; i. e.</hi> your ſinful luſts, deſires, and motions that are born and bred up with us, and are as dear to us as our natural members are; as a right hand, or right eye. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. <hi>If ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall die; but if ye by the Spirit do mortifie the deeds of the body, ye ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Mind well, and look to theſe things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Make choice of, and improve</hi> good company; yea, the beſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany you can. I count that the beſt company that is truly religious and godly, which will further us in the beſt things eſpecially, &amp; be furthered by us; to whom we may do good, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33936:58"/>by whom we may receive good. And I count him my beſt friend that will help me moſt in the way to Heaven. Worldly company I count alſo good company in this reſpect, and ſo far, as (being otherwiſe civil, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable) they may be helpful to me for the managing of my worldly affairs, wiſely and diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo as they may be moſt ſubſervient to the higheſt ends.</p>
            <p>You know <hi>Davids</hi> profeſſion and practice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.23. <hi>My goodneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to thee, but to the Saints that are in the earth, and to the excellent, in whom is all my delight.</hi> Pſal. 119 63. <hi>I am a companion of all them that fear thee, and of all them that keep thy Commandments.</hi> Pſal. 119.115. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me ye evil-doers, for I will keep the Commandments of my God.</hi> Let your moſt familiar intimate bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome-friend be, as much as in you lieth, one that is a moſt godly, wiſe, and grave experienced Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Look well to your actions;</hi> give a <hi>good Example;</hi> and the greater and more eſteemed any of you are, the more cauſe to look well to your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33936:58"/>every where, to give a good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of godlineſs, humility, gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, faithfulneſs, juſtice, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the like. <hi>Do nothing</hi> but what is commendable, virtuous, and praiſe-worthy. <hi>Beware</hi> of doing any thing that may leave an ill ſavour behind you, which may open the mouths of evil men to ſpeak or think evil of you, or of Religion; harden them in their evil ways, or ſadden the hearts of good men, or be a ſtumbling-block to weak Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that are coming on: not light, vain, fooliſh, idle, vile, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane; carefully ſhun and avoid all ſuch.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Look to your words,</hi> that they be true, ſober, grave, and ſeaſonable; not falſe, idle, filthy, vain, fooliſh, ridiculous, bitter, or railing, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4 25. <hi>Wherefore putting away lying, ſpeak every man the truth unto his Neighbour.</hi> ver. 29. <hi>Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth, but that which is good, to the uſe of edifying, that it may miniſter grace to the hearers.</hi> Jam. 5.12. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, my Brethren, ſwear not</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:33936:59"/>Epheſ. 5.3, 4. <hi>But fornication and all uncleaneſs, and covetouſneſs, let it not be once named among you, as it becometh Saints. Nor filthineſs, nor fooliſh talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor jeſting;</hi> that is, ſcurrility, or jeering: ſcurrilous jeſting, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly mirth are much unbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the gravity and ſanctity of a Chriſtian; <hi>For we muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of every idle word at the day of Judgment,</hi> Matt. 12.36, 37. much more of ſcurrilous and unclean words. <hi>And if any man ſeem to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and yet bridleth not his tongue, that mans Religion is vain,</hi> Jam. 1.26. Not but that Chriſtians may be cheerful and merry in company, but their mirth muſt be harmleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, not light, vain, idle, fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh; much leſs vile and prophane. <hi>In all things</hi> labour to ſhew your ſelves Patterns (eſpecially elder perſons) of goodneſs, truth, faithfulneſs, righteouſneſs, uprightneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in all your dealings, that you may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and gain credit to Religion by your good converſation.</p>
            <p>Let the Name of God, Chriſt, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33936:59"/>his word be ſeldome in your mouths, unleſs in an humble reverent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to do or receive ſome good; not in ordinary worldly diſcourſe, but let them be often in your minds &amp; hearts, &amp; let them be to you as hony in your months, and muſick to your ears; that you may ſay as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 139.17, 18. <hi>How precious are thy thoughts unto me, O God? How great is the ſum of them? If I ſhould count them, they are more than the ſand; when I awake I am still with thee.</hi> Titus 3.2. <hi>Speak ill of no man; be gentle, ſhewing all meekneſs to all men.</hi> Make the beſt conſtruction of other mens words and actions, as far as may be with a good conſcience. <hi>Love thinketh no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, is not eaſily provoked, beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.5, 7. Be not jealous, be not ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yet labour wiſely to foreſee and prevent evils that may be.</p>
            <p>Uſe not many words in ſpeaking, be not full of ſpeech; for as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> obſerves, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.7. <hi>In many words there are alſo divers vanities, but fear thou God.</hi> ver. 3. <hi>A fools voice is
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33936:60"/>known by a multitude of words.</hi> It is often obſerved, that even ſome very good perſons, and worthy to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured for the truth that is in them, who are of a free ſpeech, when they ſpeak of a perſon or thing which they like or diſlike, ſuppoſe it be of ſome diſtemper, are ſometimes ſo ſuperlative and exceſſive in their expreſſions, that they do ſpeak often very much beyond what the thing in truth is, to the grief of ſome tender conſciences, to hear ſuch perſons laſh out beyond meaſure, and which ('tis believed) if themſelves did, before God in their own conſciences ſeriouſly conſider, ſurely they would not ſpeak ſo largely. It is good to ſpeak always within the bounds of apparent truth: alſo to perform what they promiſe, leſt ſome others cenſure us as lyers, and ſay, as too many are apt to do without cauſe, Profeſſors will not ſwear, but they will lye, or ſtretch foully. This is ſad, and to be bewailed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Look to your aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions;</hi> love, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, delight, hope, fear, joy, ſorrow, anger, hatred, and the like; that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33936:60"/>they be ſet on right objects, ſo as to deſire, hope, love, delight, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in good things, eſpecially ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual; ſo to ſorrow and grieve for ſin, to ſhan and hate it. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Set your affections on things above, not on things on the earth.</hi> Let <hi>David</hi> be your pattern, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3. <hi>In the Saints, and the excellent, in whom it all my delight. Pſal.</hi> 119.104. <hi>I hate every falſe way.</hi> ver. 113. <hi>I hate lying vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but thy Law do I love.</hi> Pſal. 40.8. <hi>I delight to do thy will, O God; yea, thy Law is within my heart.</hi> Pſal. 119.113. <hi>I hate vain thoughts, but thy way do I love:</hi> and as <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 7 22. <hi>I delight in the Law of God after the inward man,</hi> Rom. 8.6, 7. <hi>To be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally minded is death, but to be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually minded is life and peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Look alſo to your <hi>thoughts,</hi> that they be good, uſeful, holy, heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſpiritual, of good things; (yea, as much as may be) on the beſt things, to deſire them, labour for them, love them, delight, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in them; And on evil things, eſpecially of ſin, to ſhun, avoid, and abhor them. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.3. <hi>A prudent
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33936:61"/>man foreſeeth the evil &amp; hideth himſelf, but the ſimple paſs on and are puniſhed.</hi> Be careful to watch againſt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void vain, fooliſh, idle thoughts, but much more vile &amp; wicked thoughts, envious, malicious, unclean, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful, proud, and all other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly thoughts. You read what a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof God gave <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Jer. 4.14. <hi>Oh Jeruſalem, waſh thy heart from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, that thou mayeſt be ſaved; how long ſhall thy vain thoughts lodge in thee!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Above all; look to your <hi>hearts;</hi> they are the ſpring and fountain of all good and evil thoughts, aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, words, and actions. Therefore the Wiſeman counſelleth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.25. <hi>Keep thy heart with all diligence:</hi> (the Hebrew is, <hi>above all keeping:</hi>) mark his reaſon, <hi>for out of it are the iſſues of life.</hi> All good, holy, gratious thoughts, deſires, affections, words, and actions ſpring from a good and holy heart; and all evil and wirked, from an evil and wicked heart. Make the heart good, and all will be good; if that it be naught, all is naught, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. <hi>To the unclean all things are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean.</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:33936:61"/>Mat. 12.34, 35. <hi>Out of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of the heart the mouth ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth A good man out of the good treaſure of his heart bringeth forth good things: and an evil man out of his evil treaſure bringeth forth evil things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then remember that God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſees you, and his eyes are upon you. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.3. <hi>The eyes of the Lord are in every place, beholding the evil and the good.</hi> The thoughts of ſome eminent grave perſon ſtanding by, as <hi>Cato, Laelius,</hi> or <hi>Scipio,</hi> would be a means to keep men from doing any uncomely thing, as the Heathens ſuppoſed, and ſo adjudged <hi>Seneca:</hi> How much more will the believing that the All-ſeeing, holy, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Lord is always preſent? The <hi>Rabbins</hi> were wont to ſay, that if a man did remember three things, he ſhould not ſin. <hi>viz.</hi> 1 His creation, that he came from the duſt. 2. His end, he muſt return to the duſt: and 3. the ſtrict account he muſt give. The <hi>Hebrews</hi> have another like ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that purpoſe: That if a man did think of three things, he would not ſin: <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Of the Eye that ſees
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33936:62"/>all; 2. of the Ear that hears all; and 3. of the Book in which all his faults are written.</p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Study to carry your ſelves affably, courteouſly, &amp; neighbourly to all perſons;</hi> as well to the poor as to the rich; to be beneficially publike ſpirited, and ready to do good to all perſons, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, &amp; open-handed to the poor; when they come, hid them welcome, ſit down. <hi>Job</hi> profeſſes, <hi>he did not eat his morſel alone, but the fatherleſs eat thereof, he was to him as a father; the loyns of the poor bleſſed him, and he was warmed with the fleece of his ſheep;</hi> Job 31.17, 18, 20. <hi>Humility, affabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Charity</hi> do much adorn Religion, put a beauty and luſtre on it, honor our converſation, ſtop the mouths of evil men, are pleaſing to God, good and profitable to men, gain the eſteem and good will of many, and a good report in the world, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.22. oftentimes make friends of foes, at leaſt ſweeten their ſour natures, and ſtop the mouths of ſuch as would otherwiſe be open a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Profeſſors and Religion it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:33936:62"/>
            <p>But a ſour, high, loſty, ſlighting carriage, ſcarce bidding a poor or mean Neighbour drink, or ſit down, or perhaps (as ſome proud perſons) ſcarce ſpeak to them, or take notice of them, doth very much unbecome civil perſons, much more perſons profeſſing Chriſtianity, and loſeth them much in their hearts and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and often gives occaſion to ſlight, and ſpeak evil of them, and of Religion for their ſakes. While God gives, and I have it, I would not willingly let any poor Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour go away without ſome refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, unasked, or other expreſſions of charity and neighbourlineſs; I have often ſeen the good fruit of it: and am ſure Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.38. ſaith, <hi>Give, and it ſhall be given to you again;</hi> good meaſure, preſſed down, and ſhaken together, <hi>and running over, ſhall men give into your boſoms.</hi> Matth. 10.42. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall give a cup of cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter only in the name of a Diſciple, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, I ſay unto you, he ſhall not loſe his reward.</hi> Remember alſo, that loving courteous words to them, and of them, though they be never ſo infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33936:63"/>and bad alſo, is as cheap as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, harſh, ſurly, or churliſh words, and only pleaſing to God and men: words of contempt are commonly returned in the like kind, full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, running over by ſome others. <hi>Not railing or evil-ſpeaking, but let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of us pleaſe his Neighbour for good,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.2. <hi>But what good office ſoever you do, do it heartily as to the Lord, and not to man,</hi> Gal. 3.23. Epheſ. 6.5.</p>
            <p n="18">18. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe moderation</hi> at all times, in all things, and to all perſons, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Let your moderation be known to all men, the Lord is at hand.</hi> Be not only temperate and moderate, but let it appear (abhorring vain-glory) in all things and always; ſo that all that know you and your converſation, may ſee it, and be gained by you: not unlike to that of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in Heaven.</hi> This the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts to in the word <hi>ſober,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.6, 8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. <hi>and</hi> 4.7. <hi>and</hi> 5.8. one of the three great leſſons the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33936:63"/>Goſpel teacheth <hi>Titus,</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe a moderation</hi> in (the uſe of) meat, drink, and apparel, for the quantity, the quality, and the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onableneſs; that it be not too much, too rich, or coſtly, nor too conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the world, and gariſh, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways within the bounds of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, reaſon, your eſtate, calling, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and condition of life, never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond: but alas! the devil, pride, and ſelf have ſo blinded all ſorts and ranks of men and women, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all of all ſorts, that our eyes are almoſt out, that we cannot ſee wood for trees, but take one for another, vice for virtue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe a moderation</hi> in ſpending and laying out your eſtate; if you have never ſo great an overplus, there are other ways and uſes that may be laid out more to the Glory of God, the good of others, and much more to your own advantage; whereas vain and laviſh ſpending in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, or any other ways is ſinful, and is all quite loſt, and you over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove (in caſe you ſhall ſo do) guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and muſt give an account of your
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:33936:64"/>layings out, as well as of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivings in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe a moderation,</hi> and be ſober in your deſires and endeavours after, and in your delighting and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in any worldly things, as wealth, credit, honor, preferment, eaſe, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and the like; alſo in ſleep and reſt. The <hi>Heathens,</hi> many of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Heathens taught and practiſed this leſſon of moderation, as <hi>Cato, Fabricius, Scipio,</hi> and very many more we read of; yea, <hi>Hannibal,</hi> though a Souldier, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> an Emperor, that they might not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the bounds, they would be ſure to abridge and deny themſelves of much of that which was lawful in meat, drink, apparel, recreation, Houſhold-furniture, meerly upon the account of honor, credit, or eſteem in the world; becauſe they judged it a brave thing to be ſober and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate; and a ſhameful thing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy for a man, eſpecially if of note in the worlds eſteem for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to be overtaken with exceſs, in the uſe of meat, drink, apparel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or of paſſion.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:33936:64"/>
            <p>Now what a ſhame is it, that the Heathens, Pagans, that knew not the true God, ſhould go much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Chriſtians in theſe things, which know the true God, end have his word to inform and direct them, and are frequently called on by his Miniſters, and by his Providential works to live ſoberly, eſpecially ſuch as pretend to Godlineſs; and that Heathens ſhould riſe up in judgment againſt Chriſtians, and condemn them, for being given to exceſs in eating, drinking, daintineſs, exceſs in apparel, to be as rich and coſtly in their apparel as other Chriſtians that are much above them; yea, as Heathens that are much ſuperior to them in many ways and reſpects, and be as faſhionable and modiſh; yea, as fantaſtick many Profeſſors, as the looſe, prophane, vain men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the world, as gayiſh and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh; to the great diſhonour of God, ſcandal of Religion, diſcredit to the Goſpel and the profeſſion of it, ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the hearts of the ſober tender Chriſtians, hardning of vain perſons in their vain, fantaſtick modes and ways, &amp; the great hinderance of the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33936:65"/>converſion of ſoul, who are ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their ſins, by the vain conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, carriages &amp; habits of ſuch as pretend to real piety. The work of converſion will never go proſperouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on, or as ſometimes for merly, till Chriſtians are reduced to their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted gravity, ſobriety, and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in apparel and other carriages. For what may and do many looſe perſons ſay? We (ſay they) think Religion is but a fancie, a preciſe humorous ſingularity, nothing of reality; for we ſee that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that are ſo preciſe, and ready to run after Sermons, are as cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and greedy of the world, as am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, as faſhionable, and comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the modes of the times, and as proud as any others are; if there were a reality in Religion, and they themſelves beleeve it, would they do ſo and ſo? Therefore uſe a moderation, be ſober and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in theſe, and alſo in your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, cares, and endeavours after worldly things, and in your delight in them. Be not covetous and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, pinching and ſparing, farther than is meet and commendable;
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33936:65"/>God will provide: <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. He hath ſaid, <hi>Let your converſation be without covetouſneſs, and be content with ſuch things as you have; I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither let Heathens condemn you for prodigal and laviſh ſpending or laying out for outward good things; for the back, belly, and houſe; nor for pride, vain-glory, ſelf boaſting, and ſelf-exalting; for delighting and ſolacing your ſelves in outward good things; for ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs, affectation of worldly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, and to be ſome-body in the world above others; or voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, given to pleaſures, worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, ſleep, eaſe, or the like. <hi>But</hi> if you will be ambitious or covetous, covet earneſtly the beſt things, to be rich in the knowledge of the things of God, rich in faith, rich in grace, &amp; be ambitious who ſhall go one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another in humility, ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and in all good works; <hi>Laying up for your ſelves a good foundation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time to come, that ye may lay hold on eternal life,</hi> i. e. to have a good argument and evidence in
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33936:66"/>your ſelves, that you are in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them that have a true ſaving faith, love to God, Jeſus Chriſt, and his children, and ways, to which God of his free Grace hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eternal life. So the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17, 18.</p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>Study and endeavour</hi> to be good and uſeful in, and to all your relations, to improve them for their good every way, eſpecially for their ſpiritual and everlaſting good and welfare; both for the credit and propagation of Religion, as well as for your own peace and comfort in the faithful diſcharge of your duty. There are the relations of husbands, wives, parents, children, brethren, ſiſters, maſters, ſervants, fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, neighbors, acquaintance, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſubjects, members of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth and Kingdom. <hi>It is not enough</hi> for a married man to be a good man, but he muſt be a good husband; and ſo for a married wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to be a good woman, but ſhe muſt ſtudy to be a good wife alſo. So likewiſe to be a good child, a good ſiſter, a good father, a good brother, a
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:33936:66"/>good mother, a good maſter, a good ſervant, and ſo in every relation any do ſtand in to any other, that all may be the better for you, and you for them, and God may be glorified by all on your behalf: <hi>And therefore</hi> labour to inſinuate your ſelves as much as conveniently may be into the favour of every one; of Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, by ſubmiſſion, obedience, and diligence; of equals, by courteſie and freedom; of inferiours, by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fability mixt with gravity, and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Heathen could ſay, <hi>Nemo ſibi natus est,</hi> no man is born for himſelf, but partly alſo for his friends, and partly for his Countries good, for a general good. He is not a true Chriſtian indeed, no, nor a right qualified man, that doth not deſire and endeavour to be good and beneficial to all relations. I deſire to be not only a good man, but alſo a good Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, a good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, a good child, a good father, a good brother, a good maſter, a good ſervant, a good fellow ſervant, a good friend, a good kinſman, a good neighbour, a good acquaintance, a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33936:67"/>good Chriſtian, a good ſubject, and a good member of the Church and Kingdom in which I live, and am a member, through the goodneſs of God. I ſpeak upon ſuppoſition, if I were in all theſe relations, as I am in many, that all relations might be the better for me, by being a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to one, a maſter to others, a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to others, a brother to others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oh! that the good Lord would inable and make me good, uſeful and beneficial in, and to every relation! Oh! that I could be your pattern in every relation in all well doing! Oh! how glad ſhould I be in every relation and condition to be always good and uſeful, as <hi>David, who ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his generation.</hi> Act. 13 36. and ſo fulfilled <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>all the wills of God,</hi> ver. 22.</p>
            <p n="20">20. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe Recreations</hi> when nature requires, in conventent places, fit company, and at convenient times and ſeaſons; not in times of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, faſting, or publike calamity; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver on the Lords day, which is to be imployed in holy exerciſes. Read and conſider <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.12, 13. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.8.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33936:67"/>and uſe them lawfully as recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not as a trade or calling; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh and make you more fit for the duties of your calling, civil and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious; not like him that is all day, or a great part of it, whetting his ſythe, but cuts down nothing or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. But always let your recreations be only ſuch as are lawful, honeſt, harmleſs, of good report, and ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the end you uſe them, grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſoberly, as Chriſtians. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, carding, mixt-dancing, ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous ſports and ſtage-plays are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming the piety and gravity Chriſtians ſhould exerciſe in all their act ons, if not ſimply unlawful for Chriſt ans.</p>
            <p n="21">21. <hi>Think often of, and prepare dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſuffering and death.</hi> For our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour commands all that will be his Diſciples, <hi>to deny themſelves, and take up his croſs, and</hi> (ſo) <hi>follow him,</hi> Luke 9.23. in reſpect of preparation and expectation; for, as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>We know not what a day may bring forth,</hi> Prov. 27.1. And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>James</hi> alſo, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. Therefore labour to get and clear up
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33936:68"/>to your ſelves, that you have true ſaving faith, truly repented of your ſins, and have all other renewing and ſanctifying Graces; that you have an intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, that your ſins are pardoned, the ſting of death pulled out; and all ſufferings, ſhall work together for your ſpiritual and eternal good. See before in <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And then for death.</hi> Know and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that when, where, or howſoever it cometh, it is to a true believer, to a godly man, only a means to put off the body of ſin, and to free the Soul from all ſin both actual and original, from Satans temptations, from all worldly cares, ſufferings and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, from all toil and labour, from all diſeaſes, diſtempers, weakneſſes and imperfections both of body and Soul, a paſſage from natural life to eternal life, from earth to Heaven, from the company of evil and ungodly men, and enemies, (for ſo many are in this world) to have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate and full communion with God the Father, Jeſus Chriſt, the Holy Spirit, and all the holy Angels,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33936:68"/>Patriarks, Prophets, Apoſtles, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and all other Saints departed in the faith.</p>
            <p>And though you muſt part with many things deſirable in this world, and lovely, as friends, relations, and ſome with riches, honour and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the world, yet remember it is but for a time, and to enjoy a far better eſtate, incomparably better, far better friends, the moſt bleſſed and glorious Lord God, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, Jeſus Chriſt your hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, Head, Redeemer, Juſtifier, el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brother, the bleſſed Spirit, your ſanctifier and comforter, godly rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and all the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect in Heaven; and free from all the infirmities and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they had while on earth, which ſometimes made the meetings of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved and deſired friends uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, yea, bitter, as that of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> two moſt godly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and dear friends and compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Act.</hi> 15 37 38 39.</p>
            <p>And though the body ſhall go to the grave and ſee corruption, yet it is but for a time; God will deſtroy
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33936:69"/>death it ſelf, and the grave, raiſe up the body, and glorifie it with the Soul to live for ever in Heaven in glory and happineſs, <hi>Hoſ</hi> 13.14. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4 15, 16, 17. Who after weariſome labour all day, is unwilling to go to bed and reſt? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1, 2. why ſhould any be unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with the worſe, for a ſtate and condition that is every way in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably better and everlaſting? wherefore comfort your ſelves and one another with theſe things, and in an holy humble manner triumph over death and all worldly evils as the Apoſtle did, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15.54, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22. <hi>Married perſons, husbands and wives,</hi> you know you are one fleſh, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.24. And therefore your duty in common is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To dwell together, that you may be mutual helpers one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to live chaſtly, keeping each to other only, keeping your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies undefiled: Adultery is a great ſin, to be puniſhed with death, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.10, 16. <hi>Whoremongers and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers God will judge,</hi> Heb. 13.4. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33936:69"/>
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.15, 16, 17, 18, 20, 21. <hi>Drink waters out of thine own ciſtern,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a ſpecial manner to love one another above all other perſons in the world, and delight one in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther above all others, in reſpect of Gods command, and becauſe of their near union. In this reſpect <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and God by him counſelleth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Rejoyce with the wife of thy youth, let her be as the loving Hand and pleaſant Roe, let her breſt ſatisfie thee at all times.</hi> This is the wives duty as well as the Husbands. <hi>Love</hi> is the ground of all other duties and good carriages, the bond of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, it bindeth together all thoſe duties that do or ought to paſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and wife, neighbour and neighbour. Love provoketh, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth to all duties; where this is wanting, all other duties will be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and often altogether neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or ſlightly performed, and where true love is, there all other duties will be readily performed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To bear one with another, and bear one anothers infirmities, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Bear ye one anothers burden,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33936:70"/>and ſo fulfil the Royal Law,</hi> Jam. 2.8.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To defend, protect, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve one anothers perſon, good name, credit, and chaſtity.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To nouriſh and cheriſh one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.29. <hi>No man hateth his own fleſh, but nouriſheth &amp; cheriſheth it.</hi> Now husband and wife, are <hi>one fleſh;</hi> and thus doing they do in effect preſerve their own perſons, lives, chaſtity, credit, comfort and nouriſh their own bodies. This duty lieth on them at all times, and in all eſtates and conditions, in ſickneſs and weakneſs, in health, in poverty, lameneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as well as in time of health, ſtrength, beauty, proſperity; yea, though the other party be not able, or wilfully wanting to do his or her duty; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Gods command, their near conjunction, and ſolemn Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial covenant, to take one another for <hi>better for worſe, for richer for poorer,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To be diligent, provident, &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to increaſe &amp; preſerve that eſtate which God hath, or ſhall give you: the command of God, reaſon, and your
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33936:70"/>own common intereſt, mutually bind both to be as careful of the goods of the family, as if they were their particular own goods, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo to be helpful one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To govern the children, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and whole family, wiſely and diſcreetly for the good of the whole family, and therein alſo to be help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful one to another.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Eſpecially to be the helpers one to another for the good of your Souls, uſing all loving means to win and draw one the other that is yet uncalled, and in the ſtate of nature, to grace, and holineſs, faith in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and obedience to his commandments; to prevent ſin in one another, and to preſerve and help forward the work of Grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, by your mutual hearty pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, loving advice, counſel, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, commendation, good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and all other ways; and ſo much the more, becauſe that is the chief end of marriage, and their moſt neer relation binds them, the Soul being the moſt pretious thing,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33936:71"/>more worth than the whole world, and the ſalvation of the ſoul of far greater concernment than any other thing in the world; than any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate, than bodies, lives. And he that truly loves his yoke-fellow, cannot but much deſire and rejoyce each in others Souls welfare. A duty generally neglected by moſt husbands &amp; wives, &amp; ſometimes much hindred by the other yoke-fellow; but very ſad will be the account ſuch hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and neglecters muſt make ere long to God for neglecting, much more for hindring their yoke-fellows ſalvation, neglecting their own duty, and doing the Devil, work, for ſo it is: See <hi>Act.</hi> 13.9, 10, 11. in diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging or hindring any that do mind and ſeek the good of their own or others Souls.</p>
            <p>The faithful diſcharge of theſe common duties, is the way to have marriage a merry age, a bleſſing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and a great comfort and help one to another. The neglect brings many a croſs, trouble, and often a curſe, and proves the moſt grievous yoke each to other, which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33936:71"/>be freed from as long as they live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Husbands particular duties</hi> are theſe and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To dwell with his wife according to knowledge,</hi> as is commanded 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. that is, to be able and ready to govern her wiſely, go before her, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, inform and counſel her, as he is her head and Governour. It is to be lamented, that many marry be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they know, or can govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and many husbands are much more fit to be taught and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned themſelves, than to govern others. Such muſt bewail their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and give all diligence to be inabled to diſcharge their duty, and then to do it in love, not rigorouſly and imperiouſly, <hi>Sic volo, ſte jubeo,</hi> I will and command you. Such Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage rather becomes abſolute Lords over ſlaves, not husbands to their wives. <hi>Col.</hi> 3 19. <hi>Husbands love your wives, and be not bitter unto them.</hi> Love and meekneſs ſweetens every condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and relation, every command &amp; counſel, &amp; is pleaſant to the heart as ſugar to the taſte; it makes even
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:33936:72"/>hard things to be eaſily taken and undergone, as bitter pills in ſweet ſyrrop, or pap of Apples.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To love and delight in his wife in a ſpecial manner, as <hi>(his own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy)</hi> his other ſelf, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.28. <hi>He that loveth his wife, loveth himſelf; no man ever hated his own fleſh.</hi> And this he muſt manifeſt by his loving ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to her and of her, courteous car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards her, bearing with her, and kindly accepting of her courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and readineſs to yeeld to her in things reaſonable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Not to exact or require of her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that is unhoneſt, unjuſt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, or cannot ſtand with the peace of a good Conſcience, or that is above her ability, or unfit and unſeemly for her to do, unleſs in caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. Nor forbid her any thing but what is evil and unlawful, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly, or that will be of ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, or have ſome evil effect. If her conſcience be erronious, he muſt meekly inform her of her error out of the word of God. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To bear with her infirmities as the weaker veſſel. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33936:72"/>
            <p n="5">5. To provide for her all things needful and convenient, to be libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to her, to maintain her accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his degree and ability readily and cheerfully, not niggardly, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuriouſly and grutchingly, but libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, that ſhe may, if need require, ſhew particular favours to win and incourage others under and about her. She is his ſecond ſelf, and her credit and comfort is his.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To honour her, by giving all due reſpects to her, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others, children and ſervants. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To allow her liberty being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and careful to diſpoſe of goods, and order matters of the houſe as ſhe thinks meet, as <hi>Elkanah</hi> did to <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.23. for wives are commanded <hi>to guide the houſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.14. whereby it appeareth that the buſineſſes of the houſe doth belong, and are moſt proper to the wife, as to order the keeping, trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the houſe, diſpoſing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of the family, governing the young children, and maid-ſervants; in which reſpect ſhe is called, <hi>The
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:33936:73"/>houſe-wife, Mater-familias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. In caſe there be juſt cauſe of blame and reproof in a wife, which may not without neglect of love, care, and good conſcience be wholly winked at and paſt by in ſilence, then to reprove her privately, alone, in love and meekneſs, convincing her by Scripture and good reaſon, that ſo ſhe may ſee her error, and his love and tender reſpect to her, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.</p>
            <p n="9">9. To countenance and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage her in all well-doing, commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and praiſing her, as the husband of the good wife in the <hi>Proverbs, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in her,</hi> Prov. 31.11, 28.</p>
            <p>But above all, to encourage her, and be a helper to her for her Souls good, praying daily with her and for her, minding her of the concerns of her Soul, inſtructing, counſelling, comforting, and allowing her ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and fit time for private and publike duties of Religion. It is a wicked thing to diſcourage and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der honeſt hearts that deſire to ſerve God truly and faithfully when Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Religion call on them.</p>
            <p>The wives particular duties are theſe.</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:33936:73"/>
            <p n="1">1. To be ſubject to her husband in all things lawful and honeſt, ſo far as may ſtand with her obedience to God and the peace of a good Conſcience, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.22, 23, 24. <hi>Wives, ſubmit your ſelves to your own husbands, as to the Lord: for the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is head of the wife, as Chriſt is head of the Church, and ſaviour of the body.</hi> There is a double reaſon to move the wife ſo to do; the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity her husband hath over her as her head, &amp; the con fort ſhe hath by him, <hi>as a ſaviour of the body,</hi> to protect and defend her, and provide all things needful for her. And the manner of her ſubjection and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to him, is laid down in the words, <hi>as to the Lord;</hi> that is, willingly, readily, cheerfully to obey him, by doing what he requires, and forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he forbids, coming at his call, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo far as he requires no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing contrary to the will of God: See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.31, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To reverence her husband as <hi>her head and ſaviour</hi> in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, as Chriſt is to the Church, <hi>Eph.</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:33936:74"/>5.32, 33. <hi>And the wife ſee that ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence her husband,</hi> by her inward eſteem of him, as worthy of honour on her part, as her head under Chriſt; yea, though before, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in himſelf her inferior much and unworthy, having before God and men given him by her Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Covenant, that power over her. Alſo ſhe ought to declare her reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to him by an inward wife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like fear of offending him, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly by her mild, courteous, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and modeſt ſpeech to him and of him, behaviour before him, and reſpective obedience to him as her husband.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To nouriſh and cheriſh him, and provide things needful and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for him, moſt eſpecially in time of ſickneſs, weakneſs, and the like, as for her ſelf, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.29</p>
            <p n="4">4. To go ſoberly, modeſtly, and gravely, and after a ſeemly manner in her apparel as becomes godlineſs; not gariſh, flanting, and fantaſtick, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.9. <hi>I will that women adorn themſelves with modest apparel;</hi> (mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt apparel then is an ornament, as
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:33936:74"/>well as gariſh, rich and fine, or coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apparel; and in ſome reſpects much more, and doth more win the the affections of all ſober perſons) <hi>with ſhamefaſtneſs and ſobriety, — and which becometh godlineſs with good works,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.4, 5. <hi>whoſe adorning let it not be that outward adorning of plaiting the hair, and of wearing of of gold, or of putting on of apparel; but let it be the hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which in the ſight of God is of a great price. For after this manner in old time, the holy women, who truſted in God, adorned themſelves, being in ſubjection to their own husbands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. To look to the houſe and the affairs of it, and to preſerve the goods of it, as her own, and order them for the beſt advantage; alſo the children and maid-ſervants: this is expreſly commanded in terms, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.14.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To adviſe with her husband, ask and learn of him in private: 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But eſpecially to be a true hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33936:75"/>to her husband in the things of God, that concern their ſpiritual good, according to her power. And it is a great advantage the wife hath, by reaſon of her intereſt in her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and children, and the frequent being with him and them, to inſtruct the children, mind him of his duty lovingly and meekly, adviſe, comfort and encourage him to every good work, as well as he her; one great end of Marriage, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.19, 20, 21.</p>
            <p n="23">23. <hi>Parents,</hi> you whom God hath given the honour to be fathers and mothers of children, Let me mind you of the particular duties God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of you in reference to your children. I need not adviſe you to have care of their bodies, and to provide for them in due ſeaſon all things needful for them; Nature tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that, and he is worſe than an infidel or Heathen that doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for his own houſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. but do not mind them more than God; but their ſpiritual good I chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aim at.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Teach and inſtruct your child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in the grounds and Principles of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33936:75"/>Religion as ſoon as they are capable of retaining any thing, though they do not for the preſent underſtand it; yet children do many times under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand more than we think they do: &amp; teach them a little at once as they are capable, &amp; the moſt eaſie and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental truths firſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6, 7. <hi>Theſe words which I command thee this day ſhall be in thy heart, and thou ſhalt teach them thy children diligently.</hi> (The word ſignifies to whet or ſharpen, as a man ſharpens his knife by degrees, often drawing it to and fro, ſo ſhould pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents teach their children) and mark what follows; <hi>and ſhalt talk of them when thou ſitteſt in thy houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou liest down, &amp; when thou riſest up.</hi> Eph. 6.4. <hi>Ye fathers provoke not your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to anger, but bring them up in the nourture and admonition of the Lord.</hi> A good <hi>Catechiſme</hi> is of great uſe to this end; amongſt others, Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> Catechiſme, Mr. <hi>John Balls,</hi> and the Expoſition alſo, and the Aſſemblies, are all of ſingular uſe, learned by heart, more eſpecially with the proofs; the ſhorteſt and eaſieſt way
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:33936:76"/>to furniſh children with the main grounds of Religion, and to fit them to hear Sermons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Pray often with them and for them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Read the Holy Scriptures to them, and other good Books as you have opportunity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Teach them to read betimes, and to read well; and hear them read daily.</p>
            <p n="5">5. See that they attend reverently in time of Religious duties, and on the publike Miniſtry alſo, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Repeat the Sermons unto them, or the heads, as well as you can, and God will help you.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Examine what they remember, what they have heard or read; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they will not mind, and ſo not profit by hearing and reading.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Commend and encourage them when they do well, Reprove them when they do evil. Correct them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when need requires, not in paſſion (a ſinful thing, and doth little good, yet too common; and which is worſe, ſome fooliſh Parents preſently after
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:33936:76"/>correction, are ready to take them into their boſom; this is of evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and beſides it ſhews they did not correct them in love and judgment, but only vent their ſinful paſſion;) but correct them wiſely in meekneſs and love, and let them ſee you are angry with them for their Souls good, till they melt kindly for their faults, and humble themſelves, and beg your pardon: Conſider well <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.18. <hi>and</hi> 22.15. <hi>and</hi> 23.13. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. but provoke them not to anger. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.21. Uſe not threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, nor many words, leſt when they ſee they are but words, they ſlight them, and regard not your words nor commands, nor your ſelves neither in a while, as I have often ſeen.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Give them always a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in word and deed; carry your ſelves gravely, meekly, religiouſly, and after a ſeemly manner towards them; evil examples will do them more hurt than all your good inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions will do them good. Children have a great conceit of all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent doth though bad or untrue, and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:33936:77"/>are wonderful apt to imitate them. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Let your ſpeech be always ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with ſalt,</hi> that is, diſcretion and prudence, that it may relliſh, ſavour, and ſeaſon others well. Avoid all corrupt communication, fooliſh, and ſcurrilous words, and jeſting, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.29. <hi>And the rather,</hi> you have great reaſon thus to do, and to endeavour their regeneration and ſalvation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have been inſtruments of their corrupt, ſinful, miſerable, and damnable eſtate by natural genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>If you be</hi> inſtruments under God of begetting them again, as furthering a new ſpiritual birth and life in them, and ſo of their ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it will add much to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and crown at the day of your account: But if they miſcarry and periſh through your evil example, or neglect of due educating them, they ſhall die in their ſins, but your Souls muſt anſwer to God for them at the day of death and judgment, and that may be very ſoon, and will be very ſad for you.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Buſie them in ſome honeſt and fit imployment as ſoon as they are
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:33936:77"/>capable; teach them to be good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and houſe-wives. Skill, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and providence, are alone a good portion and livelihood, and many times far better than a bare portion though great.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Be not partial in manifeſting your love to them, though Nature and Religion bind you to love them, and that tenderly. The partialneſs of many Parents in manifeſting their affections more to one child than to another, hath many times been the occaſion of very evil events, many times of undoing, ſometimes of the death of one, ſometimes of both, and ſo of all their children. There is a very ſad ſtory of this kind prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of late years. You know the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Jacobs</hi> love to his <hi>Joſeph;</hi> it was in part the occaſion of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns envy, hatred, and conſpiracie of his death, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.3, 4, 7, 18, 19, 20. Alſo of <hi>Davids</hi> love to his <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> alſo to <hi>Adonijah,</hi> and what grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous doings followed. That child whom the Parents ſo partially af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, many times proves the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents greateſt grief and trouble, as
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:33936:78"/>were <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Adonijah</hi> to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> and juſt it is with God it ſhould be ſo: and the neglected child proves the greateſt comfort and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. I grant, there may be ſpecial reaſons in one child more than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that may move and draw the Parents affections, and that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents may love it and delight in it more; as in <hi>Joſeph:</hi> but take heed of manifeſting it further than may be for both their good.</p>
            <p>Take heed alſo of being too coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering and indulging to your child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, alſo of being too ſevere and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. Too much cockering commonly ſpoils them, and makes them leſs loving, more careleſs to pleaſe, undutiful. And too much ſeverity and harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth diſpirit them, makes them heartleſs, mopiſh, diſreſpectful to their Parents, whom they think do not love but hate them.</p>
            <p>Neither be too free and liberal to feed your children with mony, nor too niggardly and cloſe handed; the one makes them proud, prodigal and ſpend-thrifts; the other makes them
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:33936:78"/>heartleſs, diſcontented, and often to uſe very unwarrantable ſhifts to help themſelves. The golden mean is beſt; a little with the Parents eye over them to ſee how they lay it our, encourageth them to husband their little well.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Teach them to be dutiful, and carry themſelves with due reſpects to all perſons. Good breeding is a great ornament, and gains love; but clowniſhneſs, diſreſpect &amp; contempt.</p>
            <p n="13">13. And when they are grown up and to be put out, and diſpoſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, to a School, Calling, or in Marriage, be very careful to get the beſt Teacher, and the beſt Maſter or Miſtreſs, for abilities, skill, honeſty, &amp; goodneſs; the beſt ordered family, where goodneſs and Godlineſs is practiſed, taught, and encouraged, and their everlaſting welfare will be furthered: And ſuch a Trade and Calling as is not only lawful, honeſt, of good report, credible and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, but alſo ſutable to your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens age, abilities, means to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age it, and to his mind and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:33936:79"/>
            <p>But in Marriage be moſt eſpecially careful to have a meet yoke-fellow and helper every way, a perſon as far as you are able upon due inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to judge, truly religious, of a good diſpoſition, of honeſt parentage, provident and diligent in an honeſt and credible calling, with other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table conveniences, as much as may be: but let the former by no means be neglected. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.30. <hi>Favour is deceitful, and beauty is vain, but a woman that feareth the Lord ſhall be praiſed.</hi> 1 Cor. 7.39. <hi>A little with the fear of the Lord is better than great treaſure and trouble therewith,</hi> Prov. 15.16.</p>
            <p>Alſo I adviſe all perſons to deal plainly and faithfully, that nothing be pretended that in ordinary ways of Providence will not be found true. They that ſeek to deceive o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are commonly alſo deceived themſelves, and juſtly. <hi>He that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth uprightly, walketh ſafely,</hi> Prov. 10.9. yet it is good providence to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee as much as may be, &amp; to prevent evils and inconveniences that may fall out. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>The wiſemans
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33936:79"/>eyes are in his head; but the fool goeth on and is puniſhed,</hi> Prov. 22.3. <hi>And if any</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>want wiſdom</hi> (as who doth not more or leſs?) <hi>let him ask of God, who giveth liberally and upbraideth no man,</hi> Jam. 1.5. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not in every undertaking to ſeek God firſt and laſt.</p>
            <p n="24">24. <hi>Children,</hi> learn to know and make Conſcience of diſcharging your duties towards your Parents.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Honour your Parents;</hi> it is the expreſs command of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.12. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.2, 3. <hi>Honour thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thy mother;</hi> ſee what forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reaſons follow, <hi>It is the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment with promiſe</hi> (ſays the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.) namely, the firſt Commandment of the ſecond Table, &amp; has a great encouraging promiſe annexed to it, <hi>viz. long life,</hi> &amp; with it <hi>proſperity,</hi> in thoſe words, <hi>that it may be well with thee, and thou mayeſt live long on the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honour</hi> comprehends Reverence, obedience, and maintaining them in caſe of want.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reverence</hi> them in your hearts as worthy of all reſpect and honor
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:33936:80"/>from you; and manifeſt it outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by your humble and reverend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour and carriage before them, lowly obeyſance, hearkning unto them; by your modeſt ſilence before them; and when called to ſpeak, by mild, humble, reverend ſpeech to them, and of them; as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did, bowing himſelf lowly before his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged father, though blind and could not ſee him, and much inferior to him in reſpect of his place and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and himſelf a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.10, 12. But wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy are thoſe children to be blamed and ſhamed, that before their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are bold, loud, ſtreperous, full of words, or ſtout, ſullen and ſurly, not anſwering their Parents, or in a ſhort ſuappiſh manner, as if their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals; are dogged, froward, pouting, rude. But moſt unworthy are thoſe children, who having gotten a little wealth, or fine cloathes above their parents, are proud, and ſcorn them, or are aſhamed to own and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their poor parents; and thoſe alſo that deſpiſe, reproach, or curſe their parents, ſuch by the Law of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:33936:80"/>God were without mercy to be put to death, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.4. <hi>The ravens ſhall pluck out his eyes, that mocketh at his father or deſpiſeth his mother,</hi> Pro. 30.17. And be ſure, thoſe children, of what age, place or eſtate ſoever, that carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves undutifully or irreverently to their parents, ſhall be paid home in the ſame kind and full meaſure: God is righteous, but he will honor them that honour their parents.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obedience is due unto father and mother in all things lawful, and which may ſtand with their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God the Heavenly Father. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Children obey your Parents in the Lord.</hi> There is the duty, <hi>obedience;</hi> and the limitation of it, <hi>in the Lord, for this is right,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is a true and real honour; reverence without this, is but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement; and this is the real and ſurreſt proof of dutiful children. This obedience muſt be ſhewed by a ready and cheerful doing what the Parent commands, and as he or ſhe commands, and forbearing what the Parent forbids. But diſobedience
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33936:81"/>and rebellion are great ſins; and ſuch perſons are counted by the Holy Ghoſt as the vileſt perſons, ſons of <hi>Belial, Deut.</hi> 13.13. and the Apoſtle compares ſuch to brute and unruly beaſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Maintenance alſo is due unto Parents from the children in caſe of want, or need, to their utmoſt ability: to viſit them in time of ſickneſs, weakneſs and trouble, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did his father, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.1. comfort them in time of mourning and ſorrow, as <hi>Jacobs</hi> children did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.5. and relieve them in their wants, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.12. and <hi>Ruth</hi> her good mother-in-law, <hi>Ruth</hi> 2.8. And this is that which the Apoſtle requires of children; to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite their parents;</hi> which he calls, <hi>a ſhewing piety at home,</hi> and ſays, <hi>it is good and acceptable before God.</hi> Theſe things are contained under the word <hi>Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Children muſt love their</hi> Parents unfeinedly, for their great love and many reſpects to them; and to eſteem them highly, as worthy all love, honour, and obedience from them.</p>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:33936:81"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Pray for your Parents</hi> dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, heartily, fervently.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>If you obſerve any fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and infirmities in them (as alas! who living is without, being frail, ſinful men, all ſubject to like paſſions and infirmities?) I ſay, 'tis your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, above all others, to bear with them, and cover them in love as far as you can. Notable is the example of <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet, Noahs</hi> ſons, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their father <hi>Noah,</hi> for which they were bleſſed, and <hi>Cham</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> for diſcovering their fathers ſhame curſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is a duty due from all inferiors-to their Superiors.</p>
            <p>There are many ſtrong and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaſons obliging children to the performance of all theſe duties; to reverence their parents both of them equally, to obey them alſo, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them, love them, eſteem them, bear with, and cover their infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe you have your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from them: you never had a being in the world, and ſo a capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of being holy and happy to all
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:33936:82"/>eternity without them. Therefore you owe unto them, next under God, your own ſelves, and all you have, and can do for them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe of the great pain and trouble in child-bearing, breeding, and bringing forth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their great pains, care, and trouble day and night continually, to preſerve you and nurſe you up, when you were the moſt weak, help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ſhiftleſs, and vileſt creatures in the world, by reaſon of native cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and original guilt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For covering and clothing you when you were naked, and worſe than naked, <hi>all polluted in your blood, Ezek.</hi> 16.3, 6.</p>
            <p n="5">5. For their continual care and coſt in bringing you up to be able to ſhift and do ſomething for your ſelves.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They intend that all they have laboured for, taken great pains and care, early and late, day and night, ſhall be yours in due time.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Eſpecially for their many prayers, pains, and endeavors in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that you may be
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:33936:82"/>born again, be new creatures, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and ſaved eternally.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Give all diligence to learn of them;</hi> to get ſound and ſaving knowledg, grace, and holineſs; to be truly Godly, and live holily; to be juſtified, ſanctified, and eternally ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Now while you are young, as ſoon as you are capable of doing any thing towards your ſalvation, in the uſe of means, before the world hath gotten room and poſſeſſion in your hearts and affections; <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy youth,</hi> ſaith the wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.1. Now you are moſt fit for that duty: now your minds and hearts are in ſome reſpects like clean white paper, free to receive any thing in, to write any thing upon. If the devil once ingrave wickedneſs in your hearts, and the world its ſinful vanities, you are like to live always, die, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in your ſins for ever, unleſs God be very merciful unto you. But if you get your minds and hearts ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with ſound knowledg and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Grace while you are young, you will be always good, godly and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:33936:83"/>ſaved and happy. Oh! it is a lovely thing to be Godly while young, to ſee young perſons breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and panting after grace and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, following hard after the Lord, and walking in the ways of God, as young King <hi>Joſiah</hi> did, and young <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>Timothy;</hi> a thing very pleaſing to God. He delights greatly in ſuch perſons, communicates much of himſelf unto them, honors them much. When you come into years, you will have many worldly occaſions and buſineſſes to mind: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, you do not know how ſoon you may die, how ſhort your lives are, and how little time you have to get that which of neceſſity muſt be had, or periſh for ever; namely, ſound knowledge of the doctrine of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, true living Grace and holineſs, your perſons juſtified by the only righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo pardon of ſin, reconciliation with God, &amp; acceptation of your perſons &amp; ſervices in the blood, and for the ſake, merit, and mediation of Jeſus Chriſt: for by Nature and your firſt birth, you were the children of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:33936:83"/>wrath, children and ſlaves to ſin and Satan, walking in the luſts of the fleſh, and fulfilling the luſts of the fleſh, utterly unable to do any thing that is truly good and acceptable to God, or to avoid evil, and the wrath to come, as the Apoſtle and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence aſſures us, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Four things</hi> which a good old ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Chriſtian, but the laſt night before I wrote this, put ſome few of you in mind of, which I will here ſet down with ſome enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To labour to get ſin imbittered:</hi> That is, to ſee and be truly ſenſible what an evil thing ſin is, how filthy, hateful, dangerous, and damnable; that it may be bitter unto you, loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, ſubdued, and mortified by you by all means, through the aſſiſtance of the Spirit of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To be ſelf-emptied:</hi> That is, to ſee how empty you are of any thin that is truly and ſpiritually good in. and of your ſelves; that the beſt performances even of the moſt holy perſons are ſo imperfect, that they
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:33936:84"/>muſt utterly renounce all confidence in them in the point of juſtification before God, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 64.6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23. <hi>to the end. Gal.</hi> 2.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To eſteem Chriſt highly, as on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary to redeem you, juſtifie and ſave you, and moſt worthy of all your love, ſervice, and obedience.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To imbrace holineſs alſo, as that which is abſolutely neceſſary to ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual life and ſalvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14, 15.</p>
            <p>To this end conſider (and what I ſay to you in this, as alſo in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer things, I ſay unto all) conſider ſeriouſly two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The torments of hell as moſt intolerable, eaſeleſs, and endleſs: Oh! to ſuffer eternally without all poſſibility of an end, or any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, eaſe, or mitigation; it is a thing moſt aſtoniſhing fully to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of, and ſee into.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The joys, felicity, and glory of Heaven, in the preſence, immediate, and full enjoyment of God himſelf, Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that for ever and ever, never to have any end, nor abatement. Such and ſo great, as
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:33936:84"/>mortal eyes never ſaw, nor ear heard, nor the heart of man can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>Children muſt learn to be mannerly;</hi> to know their duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all, and accordingly to carry themſelves mannerly, loving, and with due reſpectfulneſs and courteſie to all ſorts of perſons, even to the meaneſt and pooreſt. Good breeding and carriage is very commendable and winning.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>As you grow up in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and years, be faithful, diligent,</hi> careful and provident to look unto, and do your Parents buſineſs; the benefit will be all your own hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and you will have the peace and comfort of a good conſcience, in diſcharging your duty in the mean time and ever.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, <hi>Imploy ſome time every day in private,</hi> alone, in reading the Holy Scriptures, prayer, meditation on what you have heard and read; and labour to uſe and improve all Ordinances of Chriſt for your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual advantage and Souls bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:33936:85"/>
            <p>Ninthly, <hi>Brothers and ſiſters must love one another</hi> in a ſpecial manner, and be very willing and ready to do all good offices one for another; <hi>Love as Brethren,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, becauſe of the near relation one to another in the fleſh: for brothers and ſiſters to live at variance, or as ſtrangers one to another, is ſinful and ſhameful. What! ſhould not they love and live lovingly one with another, that were begotten of the ſame father, or born of the ſame mother, lay in the ſame womb, fed at the ſame breſt and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and frequently plaid together? If any of you be faulty (I can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe none) for ſhame let it be ſo no more; but labour to be cordially u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in love, and help one another in all well doing, eſpecially in the way to Heaven.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>When you are grown up,</hi> and deſire to change your condition, and diſpoſe of your ſelves abroad in a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, place, and eſpecially in way of Marriage, obſerve, I pray, theſe few directions, and God will be with you to bleſs and proſper you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Reſolve on nothing till you
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:33936:85"/>have firſt acquainted your Parents (or Guardians that are in place of Parents) and have their conſent and advice: you have your being and education, breeding and bringing up by their care, pains, and charge, and therefore do owe your ſelves to them; and therefore ſhould do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without their conſent and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be earneſt with God in prayer for direction, and a bleſſing on your undertaking, moſt eſpecially in the choice of a yoke-fellow. God is the great diſpoſer of all things, and moſt wiſe, yea, only wiſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Houſes and riches are the inheritance of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but a prudent wife is from the Lord,</hi> Prov. 19.14. Therefore be ſure to ſeek unto God for a meet yoke-fellow, as the gift of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let Godlineſs in a yoke-fellow be that which above all you deſire, and endeavour after to find in an helper. Never marry with one that is not truly religious; and though Religion alone is not ſufficient to make a fit match, ſuffer not your ſelves to be corrupted with the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:33936:86"/>worlds falſe gloſſes of beauty, wealth, or the like; neither croſs the rules of Nature, in too much diſparity of age, or degree, or in robbing Patents of their right: marry not with any of evil report, for beauty or lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre ſake: among all the ends of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage mentioned in the Scripture, 'tis obſerved, there is none to make one <hi>rich,</hi> or worldly great.</p>
            <p>They that look only or chiefly at beauty, parts, riches, or other world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advancements, many times have that which they deſire, but little comfort with it; often a creſs, and ſometimes a curſe with them. He that would have Gods bleſſing on the marriage, muſt invite God to the marriage: he that would have not his wine turned into water, but his water turned into wine, muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite Chriſt to the wedding: he that would have Gods favour and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, muſt ask his leave and preſence, and follow his direction by his word and gratious Providence. Be not haſty, but wiſely deliberate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate, ere you paſs over your ſelves, liberty, and all for ſo long a
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:33936:86"/>term, as during life; much leſs ſell your ſelves and your liberty, and comfort, only for worldly eſtate, wit, or beauty, though never ſo great, and be always a ſervant for theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain and unſatisfying things. And it is good to expreſs before en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, what you expect both for piety, and all other matters, of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, manner of living, order of family, and the like. This is the way to have marriage a merry age, matter of much comfort.</p>
            <p n="25">25. <hi>Maſters,</hi> you to whom God has given the honour of being Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Governours of a family and ſervants,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Know I pray and remember, that moſt of the before-mentioned duties incumbent on Patents, concern you alſo to practiſe towards your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, as to inſtruct them in the grounds of true Religion, to pray with them and for them daily, read the Scriptures before and to them daily, and ſee that they be preſent and do attend with reverence, both at private duties, as prayer, reading the Scriptures, repetition of what
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:33936:87"/>has been heard, and the publike M<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the word; and that they alſo do read the Scriptures often, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amme them what they do remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, help them what you can, and give them a good example in all things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When they do well, encourage them; reſtrain them from evil, and from evil places and company. And when they do ill, reprove them, but privately; ſhew them their error, and the evil of their ways in love, that they may ſee you ſeek their good as well as your own, and the faithful diſcharge of your duty to God and them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Rule them not with rigour, harſhneſs, or bitterneſs; uſe them not as ſlaves, but as fellow ſervants to Chriſt, with love and gentleneſs, forbearing threatnings as much as may be, that they may ſerve you out of love, and for conſcience ſake. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, bitterneſs, harſhneſs, foul lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, are hateful to God, and often do much hurt, make many mopiſh, careleſs, ſome diſtracted, and others deſperate; but love, gentleneſs, and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:33936:87"/>good uſage, hath often done much good, even on difficult natures; and your authority muſt be improved for their edification, and not for their deſtruction, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. And if they reply (when reproved) ſoberly, hear their defence and reaſons, as <hi>Job</hi> did, <hi>Job</hi> 31.13.</p>
            <p>But be ſure you command your ſervants and children nothing but what is lawful, juſt and equal, and agreeable unto, nothing that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of God, which muſt be all our rule; for ſo doing, your ſelves will be guilty of a double fault, and ſuffer moſt in the end; and I would gladly prevent your daſhing on this rock and all others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Allow them time convenient, as for your work, ſo for Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, publike and private duties of Religion and piety. It is not enough to inſtruct them, and blame them for omiſſions, but you muſt alſo allow them convenient time; it will be no let to your work and buſineſs, but a whet rather, bring a bleſſing on your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.12, 27, 42, 48, 52.</p>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:33936:88"/>
            <p>But lamentable is the careleſsneſs, and negligence, (I might ſay, the prophaneſs) of moſt Parents, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and Governours of families, who have no duties of Religion per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the family, not ſo much as prayer; but live like Heathens and Infidels, only work, eat, drink, ſleep, play, and the like worldly things, but no ſervice of God, or very rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſometimes ſome have a ſhort, heartleſs prayer at night: yea, it is to be feared, and I have too much reaſon to think, that ſome, even whom I know, and no doubt many others, and I therefore mention it, that they might ſee their ſin; ſuch, I ſay, which make a fair profeſſion of Religion, and do attend, I think, conſtantly on ſome of the beſt Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and yet have no family-du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or but ſeldom. This is very ſad, that that which ſhould be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed principally, the worſhip and ſervice of God in the family, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wholly neglected, or leaſt mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It was otherwiſe with <hi>Abraham, Joſhua, Job, David, Daniel,</hi> and all that ever truly feared God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:33936:88"/>
               <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.15. <hi>Daniel</hi> three times a day, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10, 11, 12. <hi>David</hi> ſeven times a day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.64.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Imploy them well in lawful imployments, but do not over-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them. <hi>A good man is merciful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his beaſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> much more to his ſervant.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Be careful for them, both in health and, ſickneſs; provide all things needful and convenient for them, and in due ſeaſons. Allow them convenient time for reſt, recreations, and to mend their apparel; and allow them for their work a ſutable reward; <hi>the laborer is worthy of his hire.</hi> Let poor labouring men eſpecially be fully paid for their work, whether they work with you or for you. God hates oppreſſion. Do not work on the poor mans neceſſity; you would not be willing to be ſo ſerved your ſelves. Do nothing in this kind but that which is juſt and honeſt before God and all men. Remember you have a Maſter in Heaven, to whom you muſt give an account; and there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons with God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.9. And though ſome poor labouring
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:33936:89"/>men will be glad at ſome times to do any thing to get a peny to ſupply neceſſaries; yet ſure no honeſt man, or that fears God, will work on ſuch a man or womans neceſſity: to pinch men that labour of their neceſſary and convenient food, apparel, or wages; to deny them their juſt due, defer them when they ſtand in need of it, abridge them of their neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſt, abate them in their wages, or work on poor mens neceſſity (as the manner of ſome wretched Maſters is to do) is hateful to God, who is merciful, and will ſurely avenge the poor that cry unto him, and ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſh ſuch wretched Maſters.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Teach them their Trade who are put as Apprentices to you. It is a great ſin to keep them ignorant of the lawful ways, and the managing of their Calling; a robbing of them, and fruſtrating the end for which they were put to you. As for the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, or rather myſterious iniquities many men uſe in the managing of their Trades and Callings, let the wicked keep to themſelves, whereby many to wonderment quickly grow
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:33936:89"/>rich; but fear you God. It is an old ſaying, Plain dealing is a Jewel, but he that uſeth it ſhall die a beggar: but it is better to die a beggar, than a knave; to die poor and go to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than to die very rich and go to hell, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 9, 10. The only ſure way under Heaven to have a bleſſing on whatſoever a man hath, and Gods favour, whoſe loving kindneſs is better than life, is to deal truly, juſtly, and faithfully with all men, in all things. I will not condemn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whom I ſee or hear of, that ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly get great eſtates; but I cannot imagine how ſome men ſhould get ſuch vaſt eſtates as they do in a few years, if they do not uſe ſome ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleties, or ways more than are honeſt. But they ſtand or fall to their great Maſter; I do but give ſome men an <hi>Item,</hi> God grant the faulty may make uſe of it; I touch not others, unleſs by way of caution.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Teach them alſo to be careful, diligent, and provident for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in an honeſt way, that they may ſee you mind their good as well as your own; it will both do them
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:33936:90"/>good, and make them more careful to manage your buſineſs for your comfort and benefit.</p>
            <p n="9">9. When you have a good ſervant, eſpecially one that feareth God, and makes conſcience of his ways, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem highly of him or her; bleſs God for, and make much of ſuch, and uſe him as a brother, or her as a ſiſter in Chriſt, and a good gift of God, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon v.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="26">26. <hi>Servants,</hi> you that are actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engaged, or yet free, and intend to be ſuch, let me mind you alſo of your duties, and make Conſcience of performing them, as you tender your own good.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as much as in you lieth, while you are free, or when you ſhall be free and intend to engage again, make choice of a Godly family, of ſuch Maſters, Miſtreſſes, or Dames and ſamilies where piety and good Conſcience are exerciſed, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious duties conſtantly performed and encouraged, as you tender the everlaſting good and welfare of your precious and immortal Souls. Be not ſo deluded, as for a little, no nor for
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:33936:90"/>a great deal of worldly wages or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, to neglect your precious ſouls. Evil and ungodly families have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done many a hopeful ſervant both in ſoul and body; yet moſt endeavor to get into families where they may get moſt wages, or other worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, without any regard to piety &amp; the beſt things, Gods glory; or their eternal eſtate, and prove according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and many repent ſore when it is too late, when they are called by death to give an account of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their time unto God the Judge of all the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Having made a good choice, or being in a Religious, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious family, bleſs God for it; be willing, ready, and forward to joyn with them in all Religious du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to learn of them, improve your opportunities, and continue there ſo long as you intend to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to others; if you may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, change not for worldly reſpects and advantages only, to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice in ſpiritual things.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Being ſervants, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever rank, ſort, or condition, birth
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:33936:91"/>or eſtate you were before, yet being ſervants, know, and make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the duty God and Nature require of you.</p>
            <p>As 1. <hi>Be obedient to them that are your Masters according to the fleſh;</hi> that is, to fleſhly and bodily Maſters, of the ſame common nature with your ſelves, in all things lawful, and that may ſtand with your obedience unto Chriſt, your heavenly Maſter and abſolute Lord: ſo God himſelf expreſly commandeth, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.22. Yea, though they were before inferior to yourſelves in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers reſpects, and are ſtill froward, harſh, cruel, ungodly, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. <hi>not only to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward, in all things.</hi> So <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.22. that is, in all things lawful, all things that may ſtand with Gods command, that may tend to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God and their Maſters good; for ſoul, body, or outward being in the world, not in things ſinful; for we may not think that God would have any ſervant to obey his earthly Maſter contrary to his own will and rule, who is the Supreme and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:33936:91"/>Lord over men and Creatures.</p>
            <p>And when I ſay and uſe the word <hi>Maſters,</hi> I underſtand as the Apoſtle doth, both Sexes, the <hi>Mistreſs</hi> and <hi>Dame</hi> alſo, as well as the man. And great is the benefit ſervants procure to themſelves by faithful obedience to their Maſters.</p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>manner</hi> of your obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, I muſt put you in mind of what the Spirit of God hath ſet down for your direction and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>With fear and trembling,</hi> Eph. 6.5. that is, with an awful fear of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending or diſpleaſing them, in doing what is required for matter or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: for a ſlaviſh fear or dread is not here meant or allowed, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in Chriſtian ſervants, who are ſpiritually free; but a careful reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rential fear, a fear of puniſhment or juſt diſpleaſure (as aforeſaid) is to be uſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In ſingleneſs of heart,</hi> Epheſ. 6.5. Col. 3.22. that is, truly, ſincerely, from the heart, not hypocritically, or in diſſimulation, but heartily, as
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:33936:92"/>in the ſight of God, who ſeeth and knoweth your hearts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Not with eye-ſervice as men plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi> Epheſ. 6.6. that is, not with a meer outward ſervice, only to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the eye of man, and to pleaſe man, which is hypocritical; or to be diligent, nimble, and careful while the Maſters eye is upon them, and when his back is turned, and he gone, to be idle, lazie, careleſs, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing at all, or little, or to halves, which is Phariſaical, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauding &amp; deceiving of the Maſter, both which are hateful to God, and diſpleaſing to man. A ſervant ought to do his Maſters will and command heartily, as to the Lord, with care, diligence, and faithfulneſs, when he is abſent and far off, as well as when he is preſent and looketh on, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God requires it, and ſeeth, and will call him to account.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>With good will, doing ſervice as to the Lord, and not to men,</hi> Epheſ. 6.7. that is, not only in ſingleneſs, but alſo, readily, cheerfully, and deſiring that it may be for the Maſters profit
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:33936:92"/>and benefit; which argues a good will to their Maſters.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Not anſwering again,</hi> Titus 2.9. that is, not gainſaying, reaſoning, and arguing, cavilling againſt it; yet may a ſervant, and ought, in ſome caſes, humbly to ſhew his reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the doing of this or that, or after this or that manner, when he verily beleeves it to be ſinful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, or tending to his Maſters pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and diſadvantage, as <hi>Naamans</hi> ſervants did, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 5.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Be careful to ſerve your Maſters with all faithfulneſs,</hi> Tit. 2.10. 1 Cor. 4.2. as it is ſaid of <hi>Moſes, Heb.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Moſes was faithful as a ſervant;</hi> that is, with faithfulneſs, diligence, and care to manage your Maſters buſineſs as may be moſt for his benefit, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did.</p>
            <p>This faithfulneſs muſt appear in dealing truly with him in all things, endeavoring carefully to keep, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and manage your Maſters goods to his advantage; look to his cattle, children, perſon, credit, keep his ſecrets, and do all things faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that you are intruſted to do;
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:33936:93"/>not purloining, imbezeling, waſting, or unneceſſarily ſpending your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters goods, for that is diſhoneſty, next door to robbery; not ſuffering through your careleſsneſs or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence any hurt or damage to come to your Maſter, or to any perſon or thing he hath, for that is unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; and as you deal with others, others no doubt will hereafter deal with you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Be careful to give all due reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and reſpects; hear what the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1, 2. <hi>Let as many ſervants as be under the yoke, count their own Maſters worthy of all honour:</hi> Obſerve and underſtand, that many of thoſe Maſters the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle then ſpake of, were Infidels, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, Idolaters, and otherwiſe laid on heavy yokes, which he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by the word <hi>yoke;</hi> and their ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by <hi>being under the yoke;</hi> and though their ſervitude was an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burden, a yoke, to ſerve them which were Idolaters, and enemies to the true God and Jeſus Chriſt, whom the Chriſtian ſervants belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in, loved, honoured, and ſerved
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:33936:93"/>in their ſpirits; and perhaps many of them in other reſpects very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy men: yet being, and while they were their Maſters, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſervants muſt count them, and accordingly carry themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, as worthy of all honor from them, as their Maſters, and next under God over them. And obſerve his reaſon, which is very good, <hi>That the Name of God and his Doctrine be not blaſphemed,</hi> v. 1. that is, evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by the Heathen Maſters: for if they ſhould refuſe to ſerve their Maſters, or to reverence them, though Infidels, under pretence of their Chriſtian liberty, this would occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Infidel Maſters to reproach the Chriſtian Religion, as if it taught them diſobedience, pride, and undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſs. Much more then ſhould Chriſtian ſervants cheerfully and gladly ſerve and honour beleeving Chriſtian-Maſters, eſpecially ſuch as are truly religious, godly, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious, as <hi>ver.</hi> 2. ſhews: <hi>And they which have beleeving Maſters,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And this reverence muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in the heart; otherwiſe it is
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:33936:94"/>hypocritical; and muſt be expreſſed outwardly in their ſpeech and words to them, and of them behind their backs; it muſt be alſo ſparing, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, mild, the truth, and at a fit ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp; by forbearing to ſpeak when the Maſter ſeems to be unwilling they ſhould ſpeak any more at that time. Alſo in their behaviour and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, dutiful ſubmiſſive obeyſance or courtefie to them, ſtanding modeſtly, decently, and humbly before them, uncovered, and the like uſual reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend reſpectful carriages. All which reverence and humble reſpects is due alſo from children to their Parents; yea, and alſo from wives in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, to their own husbands, who in many things have a joynt authority &amp; power with their husbands, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.33. therefore the rather is due from ſervants to their own Maſters, who are in a far inferiour condition th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n wives. Wherefore ſawcineſs &amp; bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in ſpeaking without reſpect, as if equals, replying again and again, ſtoutneſs, croſneſs, that will not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer when they are ſpoketo, or croſly, or flee away in a paſſion, or ſlap him
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:33936:94"/>in the mouth with a lye, pride in not giving the title due to the Maſter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may be, he is poor or mean, or not very wiſe: muttering and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring are carriages very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, to be condemned, though from a Chriſtian ſervant to a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Maſter; much more, if to a Chriſtian Maſter; worſt of all, if to a godly Maſter.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Patiently bear reproofs, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection alſo,</hi> if you meet with them, even when you do well, much more if for evil doing; it is both a ſin and ſhame to murmur, complain, or be impatient: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18, 19. <hi>Servants, be ſubject to your maſters, with all fear, not only to the good and gentle, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the froward; for this is thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, if a man for conſcience towards God indure grief, ſuffering wrongfully; for what glory is it, if when ye are buffeted for your faults, ye take it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently? but if when ye do well and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for it, ye take it patiently, this is acceptable with God, for even hereunto are ye called, becauſe alſo Chriſt ſuffered for us, leaving us an example that we ſhould follow him, who did no ſin, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:33936:95"/>was guile found in his mouth.</hi> See, here is Gods command, Chriſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, their own duty, comfort and benefit to themſelves, do all bind ſervants to a meek and patient bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of reproof and correction, blows alſo.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Bear with your Maſters infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; for the beſt of men have their infirmities, are ſubject to like paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as other men, as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Jam.</hi> 5.17. as you your ſelves alſo have yours; and therefore make conſcience of bearing with them in others, eſpecially in your Governors, concealing and covering them in love, as much as may be. It is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing to publiſh or blaze them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, to the diſ-credit of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; &amp; is indeed to their own diſcredit &amp; ſhame in the end: yet it is too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for ſervants when they meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to talk of, and blaze their Maſters and Governors infirmities, and ſecrets alſo, that others abroad know what is ſaid and done ſecretly in the houſe. Such the Holy Ghoſt condemneth as <hi>tale-bearers, Prov.</hi> 11.13. <hi>and</hi> 20.19. and the Apoſtle, as
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:33936:95"/>
               <hi>tatlers and buſie-bodies, wandring from houſe to houſe, and ſpeaking things they ought not,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.13. I ſay alſo, it redounds to their own diſcredit and ſhame; for who will credit or like ſuch as tattle abroad, what they ſee or hear at home? or knowingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, or willingly retain ſuch in their houſes? All ſober perſons will ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſlike and condemn ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>To back all theſe duties, and put all ſervants on to make conſcience of performing theſe duties, conſider theſe weighty Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The will and expreſs command of God, as you have heard; ſo that in a willing neglecting any of theſe, you ſin againſt God, and provoke God againſt your own ſouls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You wrong your Maſters, whoſe good you ought to endeavour hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and honour their perſons and authority.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The great reward you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, if not of men, yet to be ſure of God, who has undertaken to be your pay-maſter, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Knowing that whatſoever good thing any man
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:33936:96"/>doth, the ſame ſhall he receive of the Lord, whether he be bond or free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The place Maſters are in, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>over you in the Lord,</hi> as your Head and Governour, and you in the place of ſubjection to them; ſo that whatſoever the birth, parentage, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, parts, or former conditions of any of you were; yet now being ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants by your own voluntary choice, or Divine Providence, you muſt be ſubject, and do the duty of ſervants; and it is much better to do that cheerfully and faithfully which muſt be done, and will be much for your comfort and benefit.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The faithful diſcharge of theſe duties is a good way to adorn the Goſpel, credit Religion and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, honour the Name of God; the contrary will be an occaſion of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming the Name of God, and of the Goſpel, and the ways of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.10. and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the good of Souls.</p>
            <p n="6">6. This is one end of your calling to Grace, to ſerve others faithfully: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21, 22. <hi>whereunto alſo you are called:</hi> though the place ſpeaks e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:33936:96"/>and particularly of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing patiently for well-doing, yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not the other, but includes it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Fellow-ſervants muſt be loving one to another, and be a help and comfort one unto another in all well-doing, and by all lawful means as much as may be, that their lives may be more ſweet and comfortable to themſelves, more pleaſing to God, and their ſervice more acceptable unto their Maſter, and give one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and others a good example of faithfulneſs, diligence, chaſtity, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, godlineſs, and all Chriſtian vertues, and well-doing.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I might add, there will be a day of Death and Judgment, in which both Maſters and ſervants muſt give an account unto God the Judge of all the world, how they have carried themſelves in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations one towards another, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Laſtly, <hi>To thoſe that are poor in the world,</hi> I muſt add a few words particularly, for their comfort and direction; and I pray obſerve them well.</p>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:33936:97"/>
            <p n="1">1. If now for your comfort, you be truly Godly, that is, know God and Jeſus Chriſt ſavingly; and if you do truly deſire to believe, and endeavour to ſerve God daily and faithfully, though but weakly, as your education ('tis probable) hath been but mean, then you are rich and great in the ſight of God. God is your Father, and Jeſus Chriſt your Redeemer, Juſtifier and Saviour, the Holy Spirit is your Sanctifier and Comforter, and Heaven your in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance; all is yours, if you be Chriſts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22, 23. Bleſs God with all your Souls, ſerve him with all your heart, you are happy, in a far better condition than many thouſands, though you have little or nothing in the world, and they have hundreds or thouſands by the year, if they be Chriſtleſs, ungodly, and graceleſs, and ſuch I am confident ſome of thoſe to whom I intend this are. Fear not, you ſhall never want things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, any thing that God your Heavenly Father knows to be good and neceſſary for you. Conſider <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9, 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 84.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>He that
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:33936:97"/>ſpared not his own Son, how ſhall he not with him freely give us all things?</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.25. <hi>to the end:</hi> where you ſhall read how Chriſt argues for your comfort and ours alſo. Where God gives <hi>life,</hi> which is the greater &amp; better gift, ſays Chriſt, he will give meat and drink, which is the leſſer; and he that gives a <hi>body,</hi> will give rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is the leſſer good. He that will give a hundred or thouſand pound to his childe, will not be wanting to give him a little meat, drink, and clothes, a few ſhillings for his preſent neceſſaries. He that cloth s the field with graſs and corn, and the Lillies, that neither toil nor ſpin. Yea, He that feeds the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, kites, and other Birds and Beaſts that live on prey; God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for them, when they awake in the morning; they ſing and are mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and yet they do not know where they ſhall have one ſmall bit; and they praiſe their Maker in their kind, depend on him without diſtracting or carking diſtruſtful cares, and he provides for them every one food convenient in the due ſeaſon. Read
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:33936:98"/>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.27.28. <hi>and</hi> 147.15, 16. How much more will he provide for you, who truly deſire and endeavor to ſerve and fear him? Be not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, but beleeve. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you have not true ſaving knowledge and ſanctified Grace, an intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt; if ignorant, or unholy, and unrighteous, then I beſeech you, whatſoever you do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect, yet neglect not any longer to give diligent endeavour to get ſound knowledge of the thigns that concern your everlaſting welfare: Be diligent to get ſound knowledg, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Grace, true juſtifying faith, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely to repent, love God, and make conſcience of ſerving him dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfully according to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will in his word. If you <hi>first,</hi> that is, chiefly and above all worldly things, <hi>ſeek the Kingdom of God and his righteouſneſs,</hi> the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt for your juſtification, and the righteouſneſs of an holy and upright converſation, <hi>all outward things ſhall be given to you of God;</hi> you have Chriſts own word for it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. you being careful and diligent
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:33936:98"/>to uſe lawful means in ſome honeſt imployment.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Alas! (may ſome ſay) we are poor, have no time; all our time is little enough to get a ſorry livelybood, and poor rayment, otherwiſe had we time, we ſhould be willing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, Why! hath not God ſet apart a whole day, the Chriſtian Sabbath, or Lords day, one day in ſeven, in a ſpecial manner to provide for your precious and immortal Souls? Spend that well and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiouſly, in uſing the means to get knowledge and Grace, and you will have no cauſe to complain of the want of time. So that this is but an idle excuſe of an unwilling mind in too many. Beſides, you may ply your worldly calling on the ſix days, and yet have many an opportunity in the ſix days to think of better things, of what you have read or heard on the Lords day, and to put up many a requeſt to God, for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, grace, and holineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That, namely to neglect the Sabbath and other opportunities on the week days, is the way to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:33936:99"/>ignorant, poor, miſerable, and curſed alſo. If you do neglect God, no wonder if he neglect you; but if you ſeek him, and to your power, craving aſſiſtance from him, to ſerve him to the beſt of your power, he will be found of you, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for you, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Know, that to learn to know God and his will, and to ſerve him daily and faithfully, out of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, love, and obedience, is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary thing, abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſerve God, and ſo to ſave your own ſouls, the great end of your creation, living and being in the world; neglect this, and you do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all that is abſolutely good and neceſſary, that will ſtand you in any ſtead, or do you any good when you muſt die, and to eternity. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, no obtaining Heaven, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaping Hell. Whatſoever you get in the world, yet without true piety and holineſs you muſt periſh eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Oh! that word eternally is the moſt aſtoniſhing, to be always, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and ever in the torments of hell with the Devils; after ten hundred
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:33936:99"/>thouſand years are paſt, to be as far from an end of miſery, as the firſt day it began, becauſe it never ſhall have an end. Oh! that will be ten thouſand times worſe than to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways very poor and miſerable in this world.</p>
            <p>Therefore 1. whatſoever you do, I beſeech you for the Lord Chriſts ſake, do not neglect this one neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, to learn and practice daily to ſerve and glorifie God, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy him for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And be alſo diligent in ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and lawful imployment, careful; and provident to get, keep, and ſave what you honeſtly get, for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable being while you are here. Caſt off all diſtruſtful, carking cares, ſhun idleneſs, lazineſs, vain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary ſpending of what you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly get; be diligent and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.4. <hi>He becometh poor that dealeth with a ſlack hand, but the hand of the diligent maketh rich.</hi> Prov. 12.24. <hi>The ſlothful ſhall be under tribute, but the hand of the diligent ſhall be made fat,</hi> Prov. 13.4. Read alſo Pro. 21.5. <hi>and</hi> 22.29.</p>
            <pb n="180" facs="tcp:33936:100"/>
            <p>And be always truly thankful for, and contented with what you have, whatſoever it be, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.6 <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with contentment is great gain. Pray daily,</hi> for a bleſſing on your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſerve him faithfully, and he will provide for you. This is the way to have always ſo much as the moſt wiſe God and gratious Father ſeeth beſt for his people, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. And be ſure in what want or ſtrait you ſhall at any time be, to uſe no unlawful or unwarrantable means to help your ſelves, as lying, ſtealing, defrauding, over-reaching, for that is the way to be always poor and curſed alſo of God, in your ſouls, body, and name.</p>
            <p>I have obſerved ſome ſorts of poor people, which I cannot but much pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, blame, and condemn, as they juſtly deſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One ſort is thoſe that are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, pitiful ignorant, many of them looſe alſo and prophane, and are content and willing to be ſo, will take no pains to know and ſerve God as they ought and might, and be better. Theſe are like to periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:33936:100"/>Theſe alſo bring up their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in ignorance and irreligion, and many times idly alſo, &amp; ſo help to fill the world with perſons ignorant, looſe, prophane, ungodly, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars alſo, to the great ſhame of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and great impoveriſhing the Common-wealth they live in; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the number of Atheiſts, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons, and the Devils King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and hell in the end. The Lord open their eyes, and awaken their conſciences to ſee whither they are going before it be too late.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond ſort is, of thoſe that are idle, lazie, trifle away a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable part of their time; ſometimes half a day, a whole day and more in a week. God ſays, <hi>Six days ſhalt thou labour,</hi> Exod. 20.9. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>What thy hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.10. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſays, <hi>He that will not labour, neither let him eat,</hi> that is, do not pity him, do not relieve him, unleſs in caſe of extreme want, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third ſort are thoſe that will work hard, and as ſoon as they get a little mony, will go to the Ale-houſe,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:33936:101"/>and ſpend it there, to the diſhonor of God, abuſe of his creatures, and themſelves; miſpence of neceſſary and pretious time, bringing guilt on their Souls, &amp; diſtempers, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times death, by drinking or quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, on their bodies; and wrong their poor wives and children, who at home pinch hard for it, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might be comfortably provided for. It is great pity a ſevere Law is not made and put in due execution againſt ſuch guzling fellows, and on the Ale-houſes and perſons that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor the very ſinks of ſin, irreligion and Atheiſm, many of them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A fourth ſort are thoſe that are given to fingering and filching any thing of other mens which they can lay hand on, and fairly carry away, and think all is gained that is ſo got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: whereas, alas! they little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that for this very thing God may, and often doth blaſt and curſe that little they have gotten honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. 'Tis <hi>Godlineſs only, that with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment is great gain,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.6. <hi>for it hath the promiſe of this life,</hi> (the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:33936:101"/>good things of this life,) <hi>and that which is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. I may add a fifth ſort; ſome few, which are thoſe that having by their labour gotten a little money, either laviſh it out in ſome finery, or dainty fare, and ſtrong drink above their ability (in a moderate way, at ſome ſpecial time, is not to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.) And ſo feaſting as it were one day, and then are forced to fait or go with an empty belly two or three days after: whereas a wiſe husbanding that little they get, might ſupply their wants at all times ſomething comfortably.</p>
            <p>Thus living and walking accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to theſe and the former rules and directions, none need to fear ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther want or death, but may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably ſay with <hi>David, The Lord is my ſhepherd, I ſhall not want,</hi> Pſal. 23.1. and apply that of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Iſa. 57.2. <hi>He ſhall enter into peace, they ſhall rest in their beds.</hi> None need to fear want, that hath an All-ſufficient God, and a moſt tender Father to provide for them; nor need to fear death, ſeeing to die to a Godly man,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:33936:102"/>is <hi>to enter into peace; and reſt in his bed:</hi> none fear to go to bed, when they know they ſhall reſt.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Thus to live,</hi> (perhaps ſome will ſay, or at leaſt think) <hi>were to baniſh all joy and comfort, and to live an heavy, mopiſh, melancholy life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The world is much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and deceived. The Godly man is forbidden or debarred no joy, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural or worldly, that is lawful and convenient for matter and other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; but only meer carnal, ſenſual delights, and others, when, and ſo far as they are evil in reſpect of circumſtances; which worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, ſo far, worldly and voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men muſt and will repent of, when they ſhall give an account of themſelves and their ſinful pleaſures and delights unto God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. None under Heaven have ſo much true joy, delight and content, as the truly Godly man hath, or may have, even the moſt ſtrict and moſt religious of them. But indeed their joy and delights are not carnal, but ſpiritual; not outward in the face, voice and lungs, but inward in the
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:33936:102"/>heart, a true, ſound, ſolid joy; but the joy of worldlings is a ſlight, ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al underling joy, of the bo y, not of the ſoul, like the flaſh of a bavin in the fire, or ſtraw, it will make a great flame and noiſe, but yeeld little hear; it doth ſcorch rather than heat kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and is quickly gone and out; but the Godly mans joy is in his ſoul, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.46, 47. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.5. <hi>and</hi> 33.21. a ſubſtantial hearty and laſting joy. What greater joy can there be? What greater comfort, and cauſe of rejoycing, than to know and be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or have ſome comfortable grounds of hope that they are freed from the reigning and condemning power of ſin, from the deſtroying power of the devil, death, and hell, have their ſins pardoned, God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, Chriſt to be their Saviour, God to be their Father, the Holy Ghoſt to be their ſanctifier, inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, guide and comforter, and Heaven to be their everlaſting inheritance; and that in the mean time, all things, even the worſt, ſhall work together for their ſpiritual and everlaſting good, comfort, and happineſs,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:33936:103"/>the all wiſe and over-ruling grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Providence of God? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10. Therefore ſays the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord always, and again I ſay, Rejoyce.</hi> Such a joy as the world can neither give nor take away, nor underſtand, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.3. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.10. <hi>John</hi> 16.22.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>Yet again, p ſſibly ſome may think, this ſeems to be too much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeneſs and niceneſs, more than needs: What ſhall none go to Heaven, but ſuch as live very preciſely and strictly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I cannot deny, but many ſhall go to Heaven; yea, all that are truly Godly, and live holily, though they are not of ſo ſtrict a life as ſome are. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. I never heard or read of ſo much as one in all my life, that was truly Godly, that thought himſelf too ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtrict; but of many (no doubt truly Godly &amp; ſtrict) who have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and were troubled that they were no more holy and conformable to the will and Law of God, and to Jeſus Chriſt. Read and conſider <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Pſal.</hi> 119.5.14, 15, 16, 33, 34. and many other places, <hi>Paul</hi> alſo
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:33936:103"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18, 19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9, 10, 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſay alſo, that even wicked, looſe, prophane perſons, when them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves come to die, if the eyes of their underſtandings be truly open, and conſcience awaked, they will juſtifie the moſt holy &amp; ſtrict Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and heartily wiſh that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had lived ſo: I have heard and ſeen ſome do ſo on their ſick beds, when they had dying thoughts.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider what Chriſt ſaith and commandeth us, and all men, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. <hi>Be ye perfect, even as your heavenly Father is perfect.</hi> and what the Apoſtle ſaith and enjoyns in the name of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15, 16. <hi>As he which has called you is holy, ſo be ye holy in all manner of converſation: Becauſe it is written, Be ye holy, for I</hi> (that is, God or Chriſt) <hi>am holy.</hi> Now who can be perfect in this life, for degree, as God our Father in Heaven is Holy? And who can be ſo holy in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of converſation while in the ſtate of mortality, as Jeſus Chriſt is holy? yet this we are all command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to endeavour after here.</p>
            <pb n="188" facs="tcp:33936:104"/>
            <p>And now dear Friends and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, give me leave to add only a few choice places of Scripture to be always ready at hand, and before your eyes.</p>
            <p>Epheſ. 4.22, 23, <hi>&amp;c. Put off con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the former converſation the old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitful luſts. And be you renewed in the ſpirit of your mind; and that ye put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſs and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Wherefore putting away lying, ſpeak every man truth with his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, for we are members one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Be angry</hi> (namely, when there is a juſt cauſe) <hi>but ſin not, let not the Sun go down upon your wrath, neither give place to the Devil. Let him that ſtole, ſteal no more, but labour with his own hands the thing which is good, that he may have to give to him that needeth. Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouths, but that which is good for edifying, that it may miniſter grace to the hearers. And grieve not the Holy Spirit of God, whereby you are ſouled up unto the day of redemption. Let all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:33936:104"/>and clamour, and evil ſpeaking be put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from you, with all malice. And be ye kind to one another, tender heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, forgiving one another, even as God for Chriſt ſake hath</hi> (or as you deſire God ſhould) <hi>forgive you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Phil. 2.1, 2, <hi>to</hi> 7. <hi>If there be any conſolation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip in the Spirit, if any bowels of mercy, fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind. Let nothing be done through ſtrife and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, but in lowlineſs of mind, let each eſteem others better than themſelves. Look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Let this mind be in you which was alſo in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rom. 12.1, 2 <hi>I beſeech you by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, Brethren, that ye preſent your ſelves a living ſacrifice, holy and acceptable unto God, which is your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſervice; and be not conformed to the world, but be ye transformed in the renewing of your minds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Phil. 4.8. <hi>Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are just, whatſoever things
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:33936:105"/>are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; if there be any vertue, if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Pet. 3.8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Be all of one mind, having compaſſion one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, love as Brethren: be pitiful, be courteous, not rendring evil for evil, or railing for railing, but contrariwiſe bleſſing, knowing that ye are thereunto called, that ye ſhould inherit a bleſſing. For he that will love life, and ſee good days, let him refrain his tongue from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and his lips that they ſpeak no guile. For the eyes of the Lord are over the righteous, and his ears are open unto their prayers; but the face of the Lord is against them that do evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Coloſ. 3.12, 13. <hi>Put on therefore (as the elect of God, holy and beloved) bowels of mercies, kindneſs, humbleneſs of minde, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing one another, and forgiving one another; if any man have a quarrel one againſt another, even as Chriſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave you, ſo alſo do ye. And above all things put on charity, which is the bond of perfectneſs. And let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to the which ye are
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:33936:105"/>called, in one body, and be ye thankful. Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in all wiſdom, teaching and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing one another in Pſalms, and hymns, and ſpiritual ſongs, ſinging with grace in your hearts to the Lord. And whatſoever ye do in word or deed, do all in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, giving thanks unto God and the Father by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Act. 20.32. <hi>And now Brethren, I commend you to God, and the word of his Grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an inheritance among all them which are ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Cor. 13.11. <hi>Finally, Brethren, farewel; be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of peace and love ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heb. 13.18, 20, 21. <hi>Pray for us, for we truſt we have a good conſcience in all things, willing to live honeſtly. Now the God of peace that brought again from the dead our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that great Shepherd of the ſheep, through the blood of the everlaſting covenant, make you perfect in every good work to do his will, working in you that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="192" facs="tcp:33936:106"/>
            <p>1 Pet. 5.10, 11. <hi>And the God of all Grace, who hath called us to his eternal Glory, by</hi> (or in) <hi>Jeſus Christ, after that ye have ſuffered a while, make you perfect, stabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle you. To whom be glory and dominion for ever and ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, dear Chriſtians, Brethren, and friends, conſider what I have written, and the Lord give you underſtanding in all things; and forget not to pray for him and his, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <date>April 1670.</date>
               <signed>Your very affectionate kinſman and friend to love and ſerve your Souls good, while he is <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33936:106"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
